<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>ExoMemory - Steve Liles</title>
    <link>http://steveliles.github.com</link>
    <description>Overspill from my brain - because I'll forget it if I don't write it down...</description>
    <image>
      <url>http://steveliles.github.com/images/viking.png</url>
      <title>ExoMemory - Steve Liles</title>
      <link>http://steveliles.github.com</link>
    </image>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2011 Steve Liles. The contents of this feed are available for non-commercial use only.</copyright>
    <generator>Steve's own home-grown blog generator</generator>
          <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Creating colourised icon theme-sets with Image-Magick]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/creating_colourised_icon_theme_sets_with_image_magick.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/creating_colourised_icon_theme_sets_with_image_magick.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>While automating production of customised applications I needed to automatically create a set of icons that match the colour scheme selected by the customer. This article describes some of my experiments (details follow the strip...).</p>

<p><a target="top" href="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/--oSeeAaXsA4/TxtID4kzrMI/AAAAAAAAImI/24-smIOigfU/s1600/48.jpg"><img alt="ImageMagick comic strip made with @ComicStripIt" src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/--oSeeAaXsA4/TxtID4kzrMI/AAAAAAAAImI/24-smIOigfU/s600/48.jpg"></a></p>

<p>My aim was to find a way to take a target colour and re-create the entire icon set matched as closely as possible to that input colour, using a single command-line.</p>

<p>Lets start with a quick look at a sample icon - this was created by our UX designer and used in building the proto-typical instance of the application. It is part of a set of around 30:</p>

<p><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-e4m6fYN49O8/Txb9kVwIcjI/AAAAAAAAIg0/QqAZfCYW31I/s800/informations_contactus_icon.png" alt="Original icon" /></p>

<p>Given that I want to be able to apply a colour selected by a customer, I need to start from a neutral state, so my first step is to <em>de-colourise</em> the original icon, producing this grey-scale version:</p>

<p><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/--8FToJl9oYs/Txb5ePoLJ6I/AAAAAAAAIgc/nCX1EfMY96Y/s800/informations_contactus_icon.png" alt="Example icon to be coloured" /></p>

<p>Note that the icons all have transparency, but otherwise are largely made from shades of a single colour (a gradient) with white highlights.</p>

<p>I started by looking at the simple built-in image-magick commands. Given that I'm converting a large batch of icons I'm using <code>mogrify</code> instead of <code>convert</code>, which also requires that the command-line is re-ordered slightly, for example:</p>

<pre><code>convert in.png -brightness-contrast 20x20 out.png
</code></pre>

<p>becomes:</p>

<pre><code>mogrify -brightness-contrast 20x20 *
</code></pre>

<p>My first attempts used the Image-Magick commands <code>tint</code>, <code>colorize</code>, and <code>+level-colors</code> individually, as I was hoping for a very simple solution to present itself. Let's look at what each of those commands produces if we try to create icons with the following base colour:</p>

<div style="background-color:#0000cc; width:400px; height:60px; margin:auto; padding-left:40px;"><span style="color:white; font-family:'ubuntu mono'; font-size:20px; line-height:60px;">The background here is our base colour</span></div>

<pre><code>mogrify -fill "#0000cc" -tint 100 *
</code></pre>

<p><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-cYoe5UrvgsY/TxgphOBN5iI/AAAAAAAAIhM/LVinN-HnqFs/s800/informations_contactus_icon.png" alt="imagemagick tint" /></p>

<pre><code>mogrify -colorize 100,0,0 *
</code></pre>

<p><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-52WdHbWDsLc/TxgrS6jOpLI/AAAAAAAAIho/VhS1NSr2RNM/s800/informations_contactus_icon.png" alt="imagemagick colorize" /></p>

<pre><code>mogrify +level-colors "#000066","#0000cc" *
</code></pre>

<p><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-djRiYF9xQ_s/TxgslWJEmII/AAAAAAAAIiA/-JRBtifNU_U/s800/informations_contactus_icon.png" alt="imagemagick +level-colors" /></p>

<p>As you can see from those examples, <code>tint</code> does the best job of retaining the fidelity of the icon, but doesn't really get close to the target colour. </p>

<p><code>Colorize</code> has also kept most of the fidelity, but the white foreground has tended towards the target blue colour along with the grey background parts, though neither has really got very close to our intended colour.</p>

<p><code>+level-colors</code> has got us closer to our target colour, but we've almost completely lost the white and the fidelity of the icon is, as a result, pretty much destroyed.</p>

<h2>Reduce and re-compose</h2>

<p>OK, so we can't get there with a simple one-liner. What about if we strip out different aspects of the image, perform different operations on each composite part, and then re-combine them later?</p>

<p>This is ultimately what I ended up doing:</p>

<ol>
<li>Extract the white part only</li>
<li>Brighten the grey part (helps the later stages to get closer to the target colour)</li>
<li>Adjust the grey (background) part towards our target colour</li>
<li>Composite the white foreground back over the re-coloured background</li>
</ol>

<p>Here's the commands to achieve that (note: I switched to using <code>convert</code> instead of <code>mogrify</code> because it was easier to test incremental changes this way):</p>

<pre><code># extract the white parts
convert -fuzz 60% -transparent black in.png 2.png

# lighten the original image
convert in.png -brightness-contrast 20x0 3.png

# level colours ...
convert +level-colors "#000066","#0000cc" 3.png

# composite together ...
convert 3.png 2.png in.png -composite out.png
</code></pre>

<p>It shouldn't be too difficult to follow that. </p>

<p>The first command extracts the white-ish parts of the image (foreground) by making shades of grey - from black through 60% grey - transparent. The fuzz factor is what determines the cut-off point. We produce this white-foreground as a separate image (2.png) because we still need the original for later steps.</p>

<p>Next we create a 3rd image (background) as a lightened version of the original (3.png) then colourise it using the <code>+level-colors</code> command we used earlier.</p>

<p>Finally we composite together the background image as the base, the foreground image on top, and use the original image as a mask so that we don't lose the transparency. The final result looks like this:</p>

<p><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-V6IAdSmaJDY/TxhCqKLAarI/AAAAAAAAIig/syTquI4Dtr8/s800/informations_contactus_icon.png" alt="final" /></p>

<p>This is the best I've managed so far with my rudimentary knowledge of ImageMagick. </p>

<p>Since I'm invoking this conversion from a Java process I think I'll try something a little more low-level in Java next. I want the fidelity of the "tint" operation, with the precise colour targeting of the composite approach, I just don't know how to get there with ImageMagick.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>colour</category>
          <category>icon</category>
          <category>Image Magick</category>
          <category>automation</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Capture screenshots from the Android Emulator or Mobile Device]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/capture_screenshots_from_the_android_emulator_or_mobile_device.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/capture_screenshots_from_the_android_emulator_or_mobile_device.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>The first few times I needed screenshots of an Android app for the Android Market description I <code>alt-printscreen</code>'d the emulator then sliced the app screenshot out of the resulting image. This is a pain and - as it turns out - completely unnecessary. </p>

<p>For capturing screenshots from physical devices there are (paid) apps in the store, but again, this is completely unnecessary if you are a developer and have set up the Android Development Tools.</p>

<p>Why? Because a screenshot tool comes packaged as part of the android sdk!</p>

<p>From Eclipse you can grab a screenshot by opening DDMS (<code>Window -&gt; Open Perspective -&gt; DDMS</code>), then in the <code>Device</code> pane, select the device you want to take a screenshot from (which can be the emulator or a "real" mobile device), then click the camera icon (top right in the following screenshot):</p>

<p><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-7d2j8LBcJ0I/Tw77Op8tmJI/AAAAAAAAIdk/D-ICPn9eVQw/s800/devices.png" alt="screenshot showing the take-screenshot icon in DDMS" /></p>

<p>From the command-line I'm afraid you're pretty much <a href="http://code.google.com/p/android/issues/detail?id=13613">out of luck right now</a> unless you feel like a bit of hacking to create your own cmdline screenshot grabber by connecting to the same service that DDMS connects to.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-xNoeEFqfrDw/TxtJTtrsa8I/AAAAAAAAImQ/6gNcgm-ttwY/s1600/49.jpg" alt="Android Emulator Screenshots, a comic strip made with @ComicStripIt" /></p>
]]></description>
          <category>android</category>
          <category>emulator</category>
          <category>eclipse</category>
          <category>screenshot</category>
          <category>ddms</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[The dreaded UNEXPECTED TOP-LEVEL EXCEPTION]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/the_dreaded_unexpected_top_level_exception.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/the_dreaded_unexpected_top_level_exception.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p><a target="top" href="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-9Mgj4PvbD_8/TxtFMEPOvRI/AAAAAAAAImA/1W3xJJjaJkM/s1600/44.jpg"><img alt="Library projects with Eclipse Android and Maven, a comic strip made with @ComicStripIt" src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-9Mgj4PvbD_8/TxtFMEPOvRI/AAAAAAAAImA/1W3xJJjaJkM/s600/44.jpg"></a></p>

<p>I'm working on extracting library projects to factor out common code shared between multiple projects. With everything compiling successfully I attempted to run my apk project in an emulator, and got hit with the following:</p>

<pre><code>UNEXPECTED TOP-LEVEL EXCEPTION:
java.lang.IllegalArgumentException: 
  already added: 
    Lcom/android/vending/licensing/Manifest$permission;
</code></pre>

<p>Now it seems there's been a lot of problems with this recently due to changes in ADT, but the added complexity of Maven in my setup throws a few more spanners into the machinery. Robert Schmid describes a project hierarchy very similar to mine <a href="http://robert-schmid.blogspot.com/2011/12/how-i-got-eclipse-to-play-nice-with.html">here</a>, and actually gave me the final clue I needed to unravel the mess.</p>

<p>The difference between my situation and Robert's is that I'm using Maven for release builds and continuous integration - and so far its proving to be ... tricky ... to get the combination of Eclipse, Maven and ADT to play well together.</p>

<p>I got the dreaded UNEXPECTED TOP-LEVEL EXCEPTION because somewhere in the build cycle the Maven-Eclipse plugin is injecting its apklib dependencies into my eclipse build <em>as well as</em> the referenced projects in Eclipse. Having finally worked out what was causing my problem it was pretty easy to resolve:</p>

<ul>
<li>right-click the project, select properties</li>
<li>go to the Maven pane</li>
<li>uncheck "Resolve dependencies from workspace projects"</li>
<li>repeat for all of the apklib projects referenced by your apk project</li>
</ul>

<p>The down-side of this is that if I make changes in my eclipse apklib projects I have to build the jars with Maven before the changes are available to the dependent apk projects. I actually slightly prefer working this way anyway - I find that a little bit of isolation helps.</p>

<p>I should probably point out that I am using Maven-3.0.3, the m2eclipse and m2e-android Eclipse plugins, and the very latest SDK at time of writing (r16). YMMV.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>android</category>
          <category>eclipse</category>
          <category>ADT</category>
          <category>maven</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Setting up Maven, Android and SVN for team development of multiple applications]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/setting_up_maven_android_and_svn_for_team_development_of_multiple_applications.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/setting_up_maven_android_and_svn_for_team_development_of_multiple_applications.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>If you don't yet have your Eclipse - ADT - Maven tool-chain set up you might be interested in the <a href="converting_eclipse_adt_android_projects_to_build_with_maven.html">previous post</a>.</p>

<p>Google's ADT is great if you're working alone, but falls short when a team needs to work on the same Android project. It gets worse when you have multiple projects - especially if some are library projects.</p>

<p>It gets worse still if the development team is distributed (as we are) and/or running different development platforms - Windows, Linux, Mac OSX - (as we do). A description of how I've set things up follows this brief interlude:</p>

<p><a target="top" href="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-3U09-bd8s5E/TxtBOFAOssI/AAAAAAAAIlw/F1kSpCLv_DI/s1600/39.jpg"><img alt="Android Maven Eclipse Subversion comic strip made with @ComicStripIt" src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-3U09-bd8s5E/TxtBOFAOssI/AAAAAAAAIlw/F1kSpCLv_DI/s600/39.jpg"></a></p>

<p>The important things I wanted to enable in our team environment are:</p>

<ol>
<li>That the whole team can "get" the latest code quickly and easily</li>
<li>That the whole team can contribute updates to the codebase quickly and easily</li>
<li>That any new team member coming on-board can build <em>immediately</em> from check-out (given a short list of pre-requisites)</li>
<li>That any team member can easily, consistently and <em>correctly</em> build a signed apk for release to the market</li>
<li>New projects can be created quickly and easily with minimum of re-work <em>and</em> copy-paste in configuration</li>
<li>Componentisation (e.g. jars and apklibs) is a Good Thing, and should be encouraged by making it as straight-forward as possible</li>
<li>Developers have their choice of OS</li>
</ol>

<p>Here's how I've set things up to support these goals...</p>

<h3>Pre-requisites</h3>

<p>I am assuming that:</p>

<ul>
<li>You use some form of source-code control (Subversion/GIT/other...). Of course you do :)</li>
<li>All developers will install Eclipse and ADT for themselves as a pre-requisite.</li>
<li>If, as a team, you use Maven and/or Continuous integration, all developers will also install m2eclipse and m2e-android eclipse plugins and Maven 3 (see <a href="converting_eclipse_adt_android_projects_to_build_with_maven.html">previous article</a>).</li>
<li>You have some common practices in your team like, for example, checking out all projects as siblings in a single workspace directory (otherwise you'll have problems with sharing relative paths to referenced projects between developers).</li>
</ul>

<h3>Our Setup</h3>

<p>I've set up projects in the workspace such that all of the following are siblings in a single workspace directory:</p>

<ul>
<li>A parent project that hosts most of the maven-android config as a parent pom.</li>
<li>A project that hosts the keystore, and is checked in to source-code control (I actually use the same project for both the parent pom and keystore).</li>
<li>A (Android Library) project that contains a copy of the market licensing code (Google recommend keeping a separate copy outside of the SDK install directory). Ours is checked in to SVN for convenient sharing.</li>
<li>Multiple Android library (apklib) projects for our own code that is shared between multiple apps (apk's).</li>
<li>Multiple Android (apk) projects</li>
</ul>

<p>Since most of the maven configuration is provided by the parent pom, each new project requires only minimal configuration. The parent pom for our android projects currently looks like this:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;project xsi:schemaLocation="
    http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0 
    http://maven.apache.org/xsd/maven-4.0.0.xsd" 
  xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"&gt;
  &lt;modelVersion&gt;4.0.0&lt;/modelVersion&gt;
  &lt;groupId&gt;com.mycompany&lt;/groupId&gt;
  &lt;artifactId&gt;android&lt;/artifactId&gt;
  &lt;version&gt;1.0&lt;/version&gt;
  &lt;packaging&gt;pom&lt;/packaging&gt;
  &lt;build&gt;
    &lt;sourceDirectory&gt;src/java/main&lt;/sourceDirectory&gt;
    &lt;pluginManagement&gt;
      &lt;plugins&gt;
        &lt;!--This plugin's configuration is used to store 
                Eclipse m2e settings only. It has no influence 
                on the Maven build itself.--&gt;
        &lt;plugin&gt;
          &lt;groupId&gt;org.eclipse.m2e&lt;/groupId&gt;
          &lt;artifactId&gt;lifecycle-mapping&lt;/artifactId&gt;
          &lt;version&gt;1.0.0&lt;/version&gt;
          &lt;configuration&gt;
            &lt;lifecycleMappingMetadata&gt;
              &lt;pluginExecutions&gt;
                &lt;pluginExecution&gt;
                  &lt;pluginExecutionFilter&gt;
                &lt;groupId&gt;
                  com.jayway.maven.plugins.android.generation2
            &lt;/groupId&gt;
                    &lt;artifactId&gt;android-maven-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
                    &lt;versionRange&gt;[3.0.0,)&lt;/versionRange&gt;
                &lt;goals&gt;
                  &lt;goal&gt;proguard&lt;/goal&gt;
                &lt;/goals&gt;
              &lt;/pluginExecutionFilter&gt;
              &lt;action&gt;
                &lt;ignore&gt;&lt;/ignore&gt;
              &lt;/action&gt;
                &lt;/pluginExecution&gt;
              &lt;/pluginExecutions&gt;
            &lt;/lifecycleMappingMetadata&gt;
          &lt;/configuration&gt;
        &lt;/plugin&gt;
      &lt;/plugins&gt;
    &lt;/pluginManagement&gt;
    &lt;plugins&gt;
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;com.jayway.maven.plugins.android.generation2&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;android-maven-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        &lt;version&gt;3.0.0&lt;/version&gt;
        &lt;configuration&gt;
          &lt;androidManifestFile&gt;
            ${project.basedir}/AndroidManifest.xml
              &lt;/androidManifestFile&gt;
          &lt;assetsDirectory&gt;${project.basedir}/assets&lt;/assetsDirectory&gt;
          &lt;resourceDirectory&gt;${project.basedir}/res&lt;/resourceDirectory&gt;
          &lt;nativeLibrariesDirectory&gt;
            ${project.basedir}/src/main/native
          &lt;/nativeLibrariesDirectory&gt;
          &lt;sdk&gt;
            &lt;platform&gt;14&lt;/platform&gt;
          &lt;/sdk&gt;
          &lt;proguard&gt;
            &lt;skip&gt;false&lt;/skip&gt;
          &lt;/proguard&gt;
          &lt;sign&gt;
            &lt;debug&gt;false&lt;/debug&gt;
          &lt;/sign&gt;
          &lt;deleteConflictingFiles&gt;true&lt;/deleteConflictingFiles&gt;
          &lt;undeployBeforeDeploy&gt;true&lt;/undeployBeforeDeploy&gt;
        &lt;/configuration&gt;
        &lt;extensions&gt;true&lt;/extensions&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-jarsigner-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        &lt;version&gt;1.2&lt;/version&gt;
        &lt;executions&gt;
          &lt;execution&gt;
            &lt;id&gt;signing&lt;/id&gt;
            &lt;goals&gt;
              &lt;goal&gt;sign&lt;/goal&gt;
            &lt;/goals&gt;
            &lt;phase&gt;package&lt;/phase&gt;
            &lt;inherited&gt;true&lt;/inherited&gt;
            &lt;configuration&gt;
              &lt;archiveDirectory&gt;&lt;/archiveDirectory&gt;
              &lt;includes&gt;
                &lt;include&gt;target/*.apk&lt;/include&gt;
              &lt;/includes&gt;
              &lt;keystore&gt;../android/keystore&lt;/keystore&gt;
              &lt;storepass&gt;keystore-password-goes-here&lt;/storepass&gt;
              &lt;keypass&gt;key-password-goes-here&lt;/keypass&gt;
              &lt;alias&gt;key-alias-goes-here&lt;/alias&gt;
            &lt;/configuration&gt;
          &lt;/execution&gt;
        &lt;/executions&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
      &lt;plugin&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-compiler-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        &lt;version&gt;2.3.2&lt;/version&gt;
        &lt;configuration&gt;
          &lt;source&gt;1.6&lt;/source&gt;
          &lt;target&gt;1.6&lt;/target&gt;
        &lt;/configuration&gt;
      &lt;/plugin&gt;
    &lt;/plugins&gt;
  &lt;/build&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>An example of a pom from a library (apklib) project looks like this:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;project xsi:schemaLocation="
    http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0 
    http://maven.apache.org/xsd/maven-4.0.0.xsd" 
  xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"&gt;
  &lt;modelVersion&gt;4.0.0&lt;/modelVersion&gt;
  &lt;parent&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;com.mycompany&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;android&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;1.0-SNAPSHOT&lt;/version&gt;
  &lt;/parent&gt;
  &lt;artifactId&gt;android.util&lt;/artifactId&gt;
  &lt;version&gt;1.0.1-SNAPSHOT&lt;/version&gt;
  &lt;name&gt;Android Utils&lt;/name&gt;
  &lt;packaging&gt;apklib&lt;/packaging&gt;
  &lt;description&gt;&lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;dependencies&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;com.google.android&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;android&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;2.2.1&lt;/version&gt;
      &lt;scope&gt;provided&lt;/scope&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
        &lt;!-- made available to android by 
             "maven android sdk deployer" --&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;android.support&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;compatibility-v13&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;r6&lt;/version&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;oauth.signpost&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;signpost-core&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;1.2&lt;/version&gt;
      &lt;scope&gt;compile&lt;/scope&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;oauth.signpost&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;signpost-commonshttp4&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;1.2&lt;/version&gt;
      &lt;scope&gt;compile&lt;/scope&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;org.twitter4j&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;twitter4j-core&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;2.1.0&lt;/version&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
  &lt;/dependencies&gt;
  &lt;scm&gt;
    &lt;connection&gt;scm:svn:svn://repo/project/trunk&lt;/connection&gt;
    &lt;developerConnection&gt;
      scm:svn:svn://repo/project/trunk
    &lt;/developerConnection&gt;
  &lt;/scm&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>An example pom for an app (apk) project looks like this:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;project xsi:schemaLocation="
  http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0 
  http://maven.apache.org/xsd/maven-4.0.0.xsd" 
  xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"&gt;
  &lt;modelVersion&gt;4.0.0&lt;/modelVersion&gt;
  &lt;parent&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;com.mycompany&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;android&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;1.0-SNAPSHOT&lt;/version&gt;
  &lt;/parent&gt;
  &lt;artifactId&gt;android.ui&lt;/artifactId&gt;
  &lt;version&gt;1.0.1-SNAPSHOT&lt;/version&gt;
  &lt;packaging&gt;apk&lt;/packaging&gt;
  &lt;description&gt;&lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;dependencies&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;com.mycompany&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;domain&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;1.0.1-SNAPSHOT&lt;/version&gt;
      &lt;type&gt;jar&lt;/type&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;com.mycompany&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;android.util&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;1.0.1-SNAPSHOT&lt;/version&gt;
      &lt;type&gt;apklib&lt;/type&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
    &lt;!-- this project contains a copy of 
             the sdk licensing code --&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;com.mycompany&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;android.licensing&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;1.0.0-SNAPSHOT&lt;/version&gt;
      &lt;type&gt;apklib&lt;/type&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;com.google.android&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;android&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;2.2.1&lt;/version&gt;
      &lt;scope&gt;provided&lt;/scope&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
        &lt;!-- made available to android 
             by "maven android sdk deployer" --&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;android.support&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;compatibility-v13&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;r6&lt;/version&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;oauth.signpost&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;signpost-core&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;1.2&lt;/version&gt;
      &lt;scope&gt;compile&lt;/scope&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;oauth.signpost&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;signpost-commonshttp4&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;1.2&lt;/version&gt;
      &lt;scope&gt;compile&lt;/scope&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;org.twitter4j&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;twitter4j-core&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;2.1.0&lt;/version&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
    &lt;!-- prevent commons-logging from being included by 
         the Google HTTP client dependencies, which creates 
         a truck load of warnings and eventually kills eclipse --&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
        &lt;groupId&gt;commons-logging&lt;/groupId&gt;
        &lt;artifactId&gt;commons-logging&lt;/artifactId&gt;
        &lt;version&gt;1.1.1&lt;/version&gt;
        &lt;scope&gt;provided&lt;/scope&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
  &lt;/dependencies&gt;
  &lt;scm&gt;
    &lt;connection&gt;scm:svn:svn://repo/project/trunk&lt;/connection&gt;
    &lt;developerConnection&gt;
      scm:svn:svn://repo/project/trunk
    &lt;/developerConnection&gt;
  &lt;/scm&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;
</code></pre>

<h3>Building a Release</h3>

<p>Building a release, including running proguard to optimise and obfuscate the apk, and signing the apk from the shared keystore is now available from the maven cmdline with (as you'd expect):</p>

<pre><code>mvn clean package
</code></pre>

<p>Its still early days for us, so I'm sure there are still wrinkles to iron out, but so far it seems to be working pretty well.</p>

<p>You can start the emulator and deploy the packaged apk into it using two further commands:</p>

<pre><code>mvn android:emulator-start android:deploy
</code></pre>

<p>Enjoy!</p>
]]></description>
          <category>android</category>
          <category>ADT</category>
          <category>maven</category>
          <category>team</category>
          <category>subversion</category>
          <category>release</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Converting Eclipse ADT Android projects to build with Maven]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/converting_eclipse_adt_android_projects_to_build_with_maven.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/converting_eclipse_adt_android_projects_to_build_with_maven.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Getting Android Development Tools (ADT) for Eclipse to play nicely with Maven is quite a fiddle, involving a bunch of plugins for both Eclipse and Maven. Here's how I got it working (details after the comic-strip...):</p>

<p><a target="top" href="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-pjftaBy3xwo/TxsaQStUT_I/AAAAAAAAIlg/XqSu-Tb2OiQ/s1600/35.jpg"><img alt="Converting Eclipse ADT projects to build with Maven, a comic strip made with @ComicStripIt" src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-pjftaBy3xwo/TxsaQStUT_I/AAAAAAAAIlg/XqSu-Tb2OiQ/s600/35.jpg"></a></p>

<h3>Plugins, Tools and Dependencies</h3>

<ol>
<li>The Maven-Android plugin is <a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven-3.0.3+</a> only, so you'll need to upgrade Maven if you are running an older version. The good news for Maven-2 users is the Maven guys worked hard to make 3 backwards compatible - and so far I've had no problems on some pretty complex projects.</li>
<li>Eclipse Helios (3.6) or Indigo (3.7)</li>
<li>The Android Developer Tools and SDK (of course).</li>
<li>The <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/m2e/download/">m2eclipse</a> Eclipse plugin (supposedly not required with Eclipse Indigo, but I had to install it)</li>
</ol>

<h3>Setup and Configuration</h3>

<p>First, install maven 3.0.3 (or whatever newer maven is available).</p>

<p>Next install the <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/m2e/download/">m2eclipse</a> plugin (you might want to check if you have it already - Indigo is supposed to come pre-supplied, but that probably depends on which Eclipse bundle you install. I usually go with Classic, and did not have m2eclipse. YMMV).</p>

<p>Now update your android sdk:</p>

<ul>
<li>Using sdk manager, install all api levels you are interested in, including "google apis by google inc."</li>
<li>note: be sure to accept the license agreement for each selected jar (the ? should change to a green tick for ALL).</li>
<li>note: I find that the sdk manager either does not install all ticked packages in one go, or incorrectly reports the number of packages remaining to be installed - it "completes" but there are still pending installs (the "install N packages..." button re-enables with N > 0). I find it safest to restart SDK manager between each attempt so that it correctly shows what is installed.</li>
</ul>

<p>If you want to work with Android 3 you need to perform an additional step. Maven Central does not have the jars available, so you'll need to use <a href="https://github.com/mosabua/maven-android-sdk-deployer">sdk deployer</a> to push them into your repository.</p>

<ul>
<li>check out with git (git clone https://github.com/mosabua/maven-android-sdk-deployer.git)</li>
<li>install android jars as required by running mvn from inside the sdk deployer project directory, example: <code>mvn install -P 1.6</code>, or install the whole lot with <code>mvn install</code></li>
<li><p>if you have a shared / remote / central repository as we do, you will want to deploy the android jars there too. To do this you need to fill two fields in the android-sdk-deployer's pom.xml that the creator <a href="https://github.com/mosabua">Manfred Moser</a> helpfully separated out</p>

<pre><code>&lt;repo.id&gt;kv-repository&lt;/repo.id&gt;
&lt;repo.url&gt;scp://my-repo-host/repository&lt;/repo.url&gt;
</code></pre></li>
</ul>

<p>OK, we're done with installing!</p>

<h3>Create your pom.xml</h3>

<p>There are various ways you can create a pom for your existing Android projects. I went with the simple expedient of using mvn archetype:generate ...</p>

<ul>
<li>from a directory you are happy to create projects in, execute <code>mvn archetype:generate</code></li>
<li>you will be presented with an enormous list of archetypes - type android and hit return</li>
<li>the list should have been filtered down to about 3 from "de.acquinet.android..."</li>
<li>select "de.akquinet.android.archetypes:android-quickstart" - for me this was option 1</li>
<li>follow the prompts to conclusion - this will create a simple android project, including the pom.xml for an apk project.</li>
</ul>

<p>Once you've done that you can copy the pom to your existing project(s) and modify it manually - this is what I did.</p>

<p>(Note: If you are starting a fresh new project you can just run <code>mvn clean eclipse:eclipse</code> to generate the eclipse project and classpath, then "import" the project into eclipse. After importing your project will just appear as a normal java project (neither maven nor android natures will be ascribed). To remedy that, right-click your project, go to <code>configure-&gt;convert to Maven project</code>, both natures are added automatically and you're ready to rock'n'roll.)</p>

<h3>Integrate Eclipse and Maven</h3>

<p>OK, last part ... Getting Eclipse and Maven to play nicely.</p>

<p>If you open the project in Eclipse now you'll probably find that it doesn't like your pom.xml. When you open the pom with m2eclipse installed it will open with the graphical xml editor. You'll notice that there's an error <code>plugin execution not covered by lifecycle configuration...</code>. </p>

<p>Click the error and some details open up, including two quick fixes. Click the first quick fix ("discover new m2e connectors"). The following dialog pops up and after a short search, shows the m2e-android connector:</p>

<p><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-YeihPZ0PxWQ/TwRWknaVQeI/AAAAAAAAIas/0NnoMugrFa4/s800/install-m2e-connectors.png" alt="discover connectors dialog" /></p>

<p>Install the connector and the warnings <em>should</em> go away. Actually for me they did not - I don't know why, but I had to take the 2nd quick-fix option of turning it off in Eclipse. For me that's ok, as I want the maven build to be the master anyway.</p>

<p>Congrats, you should now have a happy Eclipse project, and be able to build it using maven as expected.</p>

<h3>What about android library projects?</h3>

<p>Well basically its the same deal. I actually started with the library projects. The main difference is <packaging> element in the pom should be set to apklib instead of apk.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>android</category>
          <category>eclipse</category>
          <category>ADT</category>
          <category>maven</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Android Source Code available!]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/android_source_code_available.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/android_source_code_available.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-CGAW8UFmRoQ/TxtLqQXEqVI/AAAAAAAAImY/PA_H2G-8N-8/s1600/50.jpg"><img alt="Android Source Code released" src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-CGAW8UFmRoQ/TxtLqQXEqVI/AAAAAAAAImY/PA_H2G-8N-8/s600/50.jpg"></a></p>

<p>I'm quite surprised it took this long, but as of 13th December 2011 the source-code for Android is finally available as part of the SDK downloads, and can be grabbed with the SDK Manager.</p>

<p>There's no jar file available yet, just a folder containing the source for API level 14 and upwards only. The Android dev who announced this stated that it is "extremely unlikely" that the source for earlier API levels would ever be made available as part of the SDK.</p>

<p>Android Developer Tools (Eclipse plugin) doesn't automatically link to this folder either, so you need to set it up manually.</p>

<p>First, get the source:</p>

<ol>
<li>Fire up the SDK Manager - from Eclipse's "Window" menu, select "Android SDK Manager".</li>
<li>Check the boxes next to "Sources for Android SDK" (at time of writing this is available for both API level 14 and 15).</li>
<li>Click the "Install X packages..." button (bottom right corner), and wait while your new goodies download and install.</li>
</ol>

<p>Once you're done downloading, head back to Eclipse and configure your Android project to use the source directory:</p>

<ol>
<li>In the package-explorer, locate the Android jar file (you may have to turn on "Show referenced libraries" from the little down-arrow icon in the top-right corner of the Package Explorer toolbar before it will show up in the list).</li>
<li>Right-click the jar and choose "Properties" - a dialog pops up.</li>
<li>Select "Java Source Attachment", then click "External Folder..."</li>
<li>Navigate to the source directory, which will be located inside your Android SDK install directory (mine is at /home/steve/dev/sdks/android-sdk-linux/sources/android-14. Select OK to leave the file-chooser dialog, and OK again to leave the jar Properties dialog.</li>
<li>Hover any Android class and ctrl-click (or place the caret on the class name and hit F3) to enjoy the source code for that class :)</li>
</ol>

<p>For the full source-code saga check out the <a href="http://code.google.com/p/android/issues/detail?id=979">issue-tracker entry</a> requesting the source to be made available (be prepared for a long read!)</p>
]]></description>
          <category>Android</category>
          <category>Source</category>
          <category>Code</category>
          <category>SDK</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Perforated postage-stamp border with Inkscape]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/perforated_postage_stamp_border_with_inkscape.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/perforated_postage_stamp_border_with_inkscape.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>This short tutorial explains how I created a curved-serrated border - such as you would find on a tear-off postage stamp - using the Inkscape vector graphics tool (v0.48.2). It is extremely easy to do, and shouldn't take more than 5 minutes.</p>

<h3>Getting Inkscape</h3>

<p>If you're running a debian based linux you can install Inkscape with:</p>

<pre><code>sudo apt-get install inkscape
</code></pre>

<p>Ubuntu users can install it using the graphical Ubuntu software centre. Downloads for other OS's can be found <a href="http://inkscape.org/download/">here</a>.</p>

<h3>Creating the perforated border</h3>

<p>First draw a rectangle using the <code>"rectangles and squares (F4)"</code> tool. Make this reasonably large. </p>

<p>Then select the <code>"circles, ellipses and arcs (F5)"</code> tool and draw a much smaller circle. Holding down the ctrl key while drawing the circle will lock the aspect ratio so that you don't end up with an ellipse.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-f7Ifgk1xqds/Tu4lanssEDI/AAAAAAAAH20/ZIkzqyhFnEM/s800/step-2.png" alt="Rectangle and circle" /></p>

<p>Next, select both the circle and the rectangle by first selecting the circle then holding down the shift key and selecting the rectangle.</p>

<p>Now from the <code>"Extensions"</code> menu, select <code>"Generate from path"</code> and in the sub-menu, select <code>"Pattern along path"</code>. The <code>"Pattern along Path"</code> dialog pops up. </p>

<p><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-Q-jYlXWOous/Tu4laEZHkvI/AAAAAAAAH28/Sz3ydQTqghQ/s800/pattern-along-path.png" alt="Pattern along path dialog" /></p>

<p>Choose <code>"Repeated"</code> in the <code>"Copies of the pattern"</code> combo, in <code>"Deformation type"</code> choose <code>"Snake"</code>, and pick a number for <code>"Space between copies"</code> - this is the distance between each circle that will be cut out from the border of the rectangle, so good values depend on the size of your circle and subjective taste. Hit <code>"apply"</code>.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-ccgBpNnVZsY/Tu4laDpsFhI/AAAAAAAAH2s/qpmSfkjxo0M/s800/first-pattern-step.png" alt="Circles applied to the path" /></p>

<p>Now we want to <em>remove</em> the path created by the circles around the border of the rectangle. To do that, first select the circles around the edge of the rectangle, then (holding down shift) select the rectangle itself and then choose <code>"Difference"</code> from the <code>"Path"</code> menu.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-XoboYeO1yHM/Tu4lZbdS9DI/AAAAAAAAH2k/ZqTIKj2oecQ/s800/difference.png" alt="Path difference effect" /></p>

<p>Change the colour of your postage-stamp shape to black (fill and stroke), then select it and hit ctrl-c to copy it, then ctrl-v to paste a new copy. Re-select the original and choose <code>"Filters-&gt;Blurs-&gt;Evanescent"</code> - this creates a nice blurred shadow effect.</p>

<p>Select the new copy and change it to an off-white colour (I went for #fbfad4ff), then move it so that it sits just a few pixels above and to the left of the original (blurred shadow) shape.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-Pgk_1jBRtT0/Tu4lZThH_iI/AAAAAAAAH2g/XeJE1jFDNZU/s800/postage-stamp-inkscape.png" alt="the finished postage stamp in inkscape" /></p>

<p>That's it, all done! Now you can add whatever content you like to your stamp and then export as a bitmap image. Below you can see what mine looks like exported as a png. Notice that the corners aren't quite "right" - this is because I didn't spend any time trying to ensure that the rectangle side-lengths were appropriately divisible by the circle + the space between copies - something that's worth doing if you want to get your stamp to look "just right".</p>

<p><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-jWvZBSpzLmA/Tu4lZKrXkhI/AAAAAAAAH2c/qrRRQYx43DQ/s800/postage-stamp.png" alt="png postage stamp" /></p>
]]></description>
          <category>inkscape</category>
          <category>perforated</category>
          <category>border</category>
          <category>vector</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Subversion 1.7 Eclipse integration in Ubuntu]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/subversion_1_7_eclipse_integration_in_ubuntu.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/subversion_1_7_eclipse_integration_in_ubuntu.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Getting Subversion 1.7 integration working with Eclipse (3.7.1) and Subclipse 1.8 isn't all that straight-forward because Canonical currently only support the older Javahl-1.6 in their repositories. </p>

<p>If you don't want to switch repo's your best bet is to go with Subclipse 1.6 and the 1.6 version of javahl (and subversion) from the official Canonical Ubuntu repositories.</p>

<p>If you do want to go ahead with SVN 1.7, here's how I got it working by switching to repo's provided by dominik stadler:</p>

<ol>
<li>Add dominik's repository: <code>sudo apt-add-repository ppa:dominik-stadler/subversion-1.7</code></li>
<li>Update apt: <code>sudo apt-get update</code></li>
<li>Install libsvn-java: <code>sudo apt-get install libsvn-java</code></li>
<li>Install subversion 1.7: <code>sudo apt-get install subversion</code></li>
</ol>

<p>To enable Eclipse to see your libsvn-java installation, go to the eclipse install directory (I install in <code>/home/steve/dev/tools/eclipse</code>) and edit the eclipse.ini file. </p>

<p>You need to add <code>-Djava.library.path=/usr/lib/jni</code>, which is where libsvn-java's native libraries get installed. Add it immediately following <code>-vmargs</code>. My eclipse.ini file now looks like this:</p>

<pre><code>-startup
plugins/org.eclipse.equinox.launcher_1.2.0.v20110502.jar
--launcher.library
plugins/org.eclipse.equinox.launcher.gtk.linux.x86_64_1.1.100.v20110505
-showsplash
org.eclipse.platform
--launcher.XXMaxPermSize
256m
--launcher.defaultAction
openFile
-vmargs
-Djava.library.path=/usr/lib/jni
-Xms40m
-Xmx600m
</code></pre>

<p>If you use Subclipse but never previously installed Javahl you probably see irritating warning dialogs the first time you do <em>anything</em> in Eclipse after a restart. Installing javahl correctly will prevent those :). </p>

<p><a href="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-KJtp8zUoqwQ/TxtOTq8hF-I/AAAAAAAAImw/fdzs2yeDUxw/s1600/53.jpg"><img alt="Eclipse, SVN and Ubuntu - Javahl, all playing nicely - a comic strip made with @ComicStripIt" src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-KJtp8zUoqwQ/TxtOTq8hF-I/AAAAAAAAImw/fdzs2yeDUxw/s600/53.jpg"></a></p>

<p>Merry Christmas!</p>
]]></description>
          <category>ubuntu</category>
          <category>eclipse</category>
          <category>subversion</category>
          <category>javahl</category>
          <category>subclipse</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Google and rel=author - not a level playing field]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/google_and_rel_author_not_a_level_playing_field.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/google_and_rel_author_not_a_level_playing_field.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>If you've read my earlier post documenting my attempts to get Google to recognize my <a href="microformats_rich_snippets_rel_author_and_search_listings.html">rel=author</a> markup you'll see that I expended quite a bit of effort trying to get my mugshot to appear with search result listings for my blog pages. Here's what I'm aiming for:</p>

<p><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-DKGP9ZJF8G0/Ts7aVKcwJiI/AAAAAAAAHyE/ZHCauxKCvYM/s600/rich-snippets-search-listing.png" alt="rich-snippets test tool example of how search-result listings could look" /></p>

<p>Its been more than a month now, and the Googlebot has crawled my site many times, but still no mugshots. </p>

<p>Just lately I'm starting to think that there's absolutely nothing wrong with how I've marked up my content (this is confirmed by Google's rich-snippets testing tool as you can see in the screen-shot above). Rather I'm beginning to suspect a minor evil (or stupidity) is at play.</p>

<h3>rel=author: The small-print</h3>

<p>My suspicions were aroused on my latest re-reading of Google's documentation on rel=author. There are three things that struck me on this re-reading:</p>

<p>First, on the subject of your Google Profile picture, Google have this to say:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>"you'll need a Google Profile with a good, recognizable headshot as your profile photo"</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Mm, ok, well my profile pic is a headshot, and (I think) is pretty recognizable... but what, in Google's subjective judgement, is a "good" photo?</p>

<p>Second, and more ominously:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>"Google doesn't guarantee to show author information in Google Web Search or Google News results."</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Riiiight. Here's the thing: when do Google actually show author information? Is it based on something algorithmic as you might expect from Google (e.g. PageRank), or is it a subjective human judgement?</p>

<p>Finally:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>"Once you're done, please complete this <a href="https://spreadsheets.google.com/a/google.com/spreadsheet/viewform?formkey=dHdCLVRwcTlvOWFKQXhNbEgtbE10QVE6MQ">form</a> so we can let you know of any implementation issues. While we won't be able to individually reply to everyone who fills out this form, we may be in touch with questions about your data."</p>
</blockquote>

<p>OK, so this suggests that there actually may be a human in the loop, and google are actively white-listing sites for inclusion of author information. </p>

<p>I hope this is the case, because that would mean at least some small chance that my authorship info will <em>eventually</em> appear in search result listings.</p>

<h3>page-rank: The rich get richer</h3>

<p>Right now - perhaps somewhat pessimistically - I'm guessing that Google will show authorship information if you already have a sufficiently high page-rank (I've no idea what rank is required, but I'm pretty sure I'm a long way below it). </p>

<p>Here's why I think that:</p>

<ol>
<li>It would be very un-Google-like - not to mention unscalable - to have a human in the loop making subjective judgements.</li>
<li>Page-rank gives Google a heuristic on which to judge the quality of a site, and they (understandably) want to promote high-quality sites more vigourously.</li>
</ol>

<h3>Google: Evil, or just stupid?</h3>

<p>And here's why I think that is borderline evil, or at least stupid: it creates a situation where the already popular gain even more popularity, and the rest of us fade even further into obscurity. Its an example of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greedy_algorithm">greedy algorithm</a> at work. </p>

<p>Come on Google - I'm following your rules to the letter, working hard to make the web a better place and helping you to better <a href="http://www.google.com/about/corporate/company/">organise the world's information</a>, why aren't you taking advantage of that?</p>

<h3>Conclusion: It's all just speculation</h3>

<p>Actually my only real problem with all this is that it isn't clear how, when or why authorship information will or will not be used, which leads to the sort of speculation I've presented in this article. </p>

<p>If it were possible to understand definitively why my authorship information isn't showing I could potentially do something about it instead of spinning my wheels guessing how to make it work (and whining about it :)).</p>
]]></description>
          <category>google</category>
          <category>good-evil-stupid?</category>
          <category>rel=author</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Another Google Chrome CSS bug]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/another_google_chrome_css_bug.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/another_google_chrome_css_bug.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p><style>
.legible { text-rendering:optimizelegibility; }
.shadow { box-shadow: 0px 0px 20px black;}
</style>
Since I moved my blog from blogger I've noticed on many occasions that Chrome would screw up the text rendering on the first view of a page. Hit F5 to refresh and it goes away. For a long time I thought this was related to my use of web-fonts (the excellent <a href="http://www.google.com/webfonts#ChoosePlace:select">Google Web Fonts</a>, but in fact its simpler than that.</p>

<p>Eventually I took the time to look into it a bit more, and narrowed it down to the fact that I am using the <code>text-rendering:optimizeLegibility</code> css directive, which does make a nice difference to the kerning of the fixed-width fonts I'm using (<code>Ubuntu Mono</code>), but also has the apparent side-effect of setting negative margins on those fixed-width texts which make them run into/over surrounding text.</p>

<p>Once I'd figured out what was causing my problem a quick Google search showed I'm not alone. The chromium issue tracker has several relevant bug reports. I chose to add my tuppence to <a href="http://code.google.com/p/chromium/issues/detail?id=96936#c16">bug 96936</a></p>

<h3>Examples of the bug</h3>

<p>Here's what the problem looks like when <code>text-rendering:optimizeLegibility</code> is in use in Chrome 15 (and the as yet unreleased 16 beta):</p>

<p><img class="shadow" title="With 'text-rendering:optimizeLegibility'" src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-T5peLzltfzU/TupN9gwMcoI/AAAAAAAAH18/_CDK0F-qh2Q/s600/text-rendering.png"></p>

<p>And here (and also now in the blog you are reading) is how it looks without optimizeLegibility:</p>

<p><img class="shadow" title="Without 'text-rendering:optimizeLegibility'" src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-sK4tre7Q8dc/TupN-4pchhI/AAAAAAAAH2E/7WYdEGb3kKk/s600/not-text-rendering.png"></p>

<p>If you are reading this in Google Chrome you can check to see if the bug still exists by taking a look at the example text below, which is taken from the sample I submitted to <a href="http://code.google.com/p/chromium/issues/detail?id=96936#c16">bug 96936</a>. If you see overlapping characters below, the bug is not fixed in your version of Chrome.</p>

<div class="example legible">
  <p>Code blocks inside paragraphs like <code>this</code> don't <code>look</code> very <code>nice</code> with text-rendering set to optimizeLegibility.</p>
</div>

<p><em>Note</em>: Some interesting characteristics of the bug include:</p>

<ol>
<li>Text renders correctly if you refresh the page after the initial visit</li>
<li>It appears much worse with certain fonts - fixed-width/monospace fonts in particular seem to suffer</li>
<li>The width of the text appears to be calculated incorrectly, not just margins - you can see this in the first screen-shot where the date tab cuts into the end of "2011".</li>
</ol>
]]></description>
          <category>css</category>
          <category>chrome</category>
          <category>bug</category>
          <category>font</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Google Chrome CSS bug]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/google_chrome_css_bug.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/google_chrome_css_bug.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p><style>
.s1 { display:inline; }
.s2 { display:table; }
</style>
Today while working on a project that uses <code>contenteditable &lt;div&gt;</code> elements I got stuck on a bug for a good long time because of the crazy failure-mode it exhibited. You can try for yourself in the <code>contenteditable</code> below (sooner or later I hope this bug will be fixed and the example will stop working :)).</p>

<div class="example">
  <div class="s1 s2" contenteditable="true">Try deleting the first character in this sentence (you won't be able to), or the last (the caret will disappear after deleting the character)</div>
</div>

<p>I'm working on a reasonably complex editor using Google Web Toolkit (GWT) with multiple content-editable <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> elements used to collect text input. You might be wondering why we're using <code>contenteditable</code> instead of <code>&lt;textarea&gt;</code> or something - well here's why:</p>

<ol>
<li>Styling <code>contenteditable</code>'s is much easier</li>
<li>Allowing the input area to grow to fit the contained content "just works" - this is pretty hard to do with a <code>&lt;textarea&gt;</code>, though it can be done.</li>
<li>We can deliberately insert html into the <code>contenteditable</code> as the user types - for example i'm creating a tag editor, and by using a <code>contenteditable</code> I can render the tags nicely even as the user is typing - say, whenever the user enters a delimiter.</li>
</ol>

<p>Of course, <code>contenteditable</code>'s are not without problems - not least you have to deal with the html content that they produce (e.g. <code>&lt;p&gt;</code> or <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> tags produced by the enter key), and arbitrary html resulting from paste operations, but that's another story.</p>

<h2>How the bug manifests</h2>

<p>Anyways, I have a bunch of <code>contenteditable</code>'s in my web-app, all seemingly working fine. Then I notice that <em>one</em> of them is behaving a bit strangely: if I try to delete characters from the end of the content the <code>contenteditable</code> loses focus after deleting one character. </p>

<p>Being a complex app I have all kinds of event-handlers bound to these <code>contenteditable</code>'s, so I started removing the likely suspects one by one, trying to find the culprit.</p>

<p>Eventually I'd removed all the event-handlers and was scratching my head, wondering how on earth I could still have this problem on just one of my <code>contenteditable</code>'s. </p>

<p>I checked in Firefox - no problem, all working. I compiled the GWT app to pure javascript and ran outside of GWT development mode, just to be sure it wasn't some weird GWT-chrome-plugin bug - still suffering. I looked for other event handlers bound higher up the DOM tree. Still no joy.</p>

<h2>When the bug manifests</h2>

<p>Finally - almost in desperation - I started inspecting the CSS (surely the CSS could not be causing such bizarre behaviour, right? Uh, wrong!).</p>

<p>After some puzzling I reduced the replication steps down to some very simple html and an unfortunate collision of CSS styles:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;bug&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;style&gt;
      .s1 { display:inline; }
      .s2 { display:table; }
    &lt;/style&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;div class="s1 s2" contenteditable="true"&gt;delete me&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Of course this CSS doesn't make sense - the two <code>display</code> settings conflict. That's easy to spot in a simple example like this, but much more difficult in a complex application with a large DOM tree and many many CSS styles. </p>

<p>As for the failure mode, you might expect one style to "win", and forgivably it could be a different style in different browsers. </p>

<p>What you really <em>don't</em> expect is the bizarre behaviour we experienced. The bug currently manifests in Chrome 15 (and 16 beta) on Linux, Mac and Windows(7), and is reported in the chromium issue tracker as <a href="http://code.google.com/p/chromium/issues/detail?id=107366">bug 107366</a>.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>css</category>
          <category>chrome</category>
          <category>bug</category>
          <category>contenteditable</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Hosting a static website in Amazon S3]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/hosting_a_static_website_in_amazon_s3.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/hosting_a_static_website_in_amazon_s3.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Amazon Simple Storage Service - S3 - can be used to host a static web-site, but it isn't immediately obvious how to set this up. Here's how I did it (I'm using the standard AWS console for this):</p>

<h4>Step-1: If you haven't already, sign up for Amazon S3</h4>

<h4>Step-2: Log-in to the AWS console, and go to the S3 Tab</h4>

<h4>Step-3: Create an S3 bucket:</h4>

<p>It doesn't really matter what name you give your bucket unless you plan to <a href="pointing_a_domain_name_to_an_amazon_s3_bucket.html">forward a domain name to your S3 hosted site</a> </p>

<p><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-ntmu1ROjx_k/TtEulvLq2qI/AAAAAAAAHy0/kAz8dljKeMU/s578/create-bucket.png" alt="Create a bucket" /></p>

<h4>Step-4: Upload your static site to the bucket</h4>

<p>Select your bucket in the "Buckets" pane, then right-click in the "Objects and Folders" pane and choose "upload". If you are uploading many folders you'll probably want to use the "enhanced" uploader applet.</p>

<h4>Step-5: Set your bucket to be a website:</h4>

<p>First, right-click on your bucket in the "Buckets" pane (far left) and choose "Properties".</p>

<p><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-5qHHItMStOU/TtEumMeQGeI/AAAAAAAAHzA/3HSscD7aFr0/s426/bucket-properties.png" alt="Open Bucket Properties" /></p>

<p>The properties of your bucket will appear in the "Properties" pane at the bottom of the screen.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-4B_VhzIeRjw/TtEzQSqQdUI/AAAAAAAAHzY/EcMc-2ruk98/s600/bucket-properties-tabs.png" alt="Bucket Properties" /></p>

<p>In the bucket propertes go to the "Website" tab. Make sure to:</p>

<ol>
<li>Check the "enabled" box</li>
<li>Enter the name of an "index document" in the box (this will be page that should be loaded if someone visits the root of your bucket - websites typically us index.html).</li>
<li>Note the "endpoint" url - this will be the url to your website.</li>
</ol>

<p><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-poLROP8Apoc/TtE1Fn9kH2I/AAAAAAAAH0M/XQJ1XrGLoS8/s600/bucket-properties-website.png" alt="Bucket Properties Website Tab" /></p>

<p>If you open the endpoint url in a separate tab in your browser now you will see permission denied errors, so lets fix that...</p>

<h4>Step-6: Make your web-site accessable to viewers:</h4>

<ol>
<li>Still in the bucket "Properties" pane, open the "Permissions" tab and click "Edit Bucket Policy" - a window pops up.</li>
<li>Paste in the code from the box below, replacing <code>mybucketname</code> with, well, your bucket name :)</li>
<li>Click <code>save</code> and your done - go visit that end-point url which should now be hosting your static website :)</li>
</ol>

<p>Here's the permissions policy you need - don't forget to change <code>mybucketname</code>!</p>

<pre><code>{
    "Version": "2008-10-17",
    "Statement": [{
        "Sid": "PublicReadForGetBucketObjects",
        "Effect": "Allow",
        "Principal": {
            "AWS": "*"
        },
        "Action": "s3:GetObject",
        "Resource": "arn:aws:s3:::mybucketname/*"
    }]
}
</code></pre>

<p><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-loUsJEs3JC4/TtEulGDjuEI/AAAAAAAAHyw/Q1QYKwZY5WQ/s600/bucket-policy-edit.png" alt="Edit Bucket Policy" /></p>

<h4>Step-7: Registered a domain-name? Point it at your S3 hosted website...</h4>

<p>See my other post on <a href="pointing_a_domain_name_to_an_amazon_s3_bucket.html">how to forward a domain name to an S3 bucket</a>.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>static</category>
          <category>website</category>
          <category>amazon</category>
          <category>S3</category>
          <category>hosting</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Plus-One any page - Google +1 Bookmarklet]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/plus_one_any_page_google_1_bookmarklet.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/plus_one_any_page_google_1_bookmarklet.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Many pages that you might want to share don't have <code>Google+</code> <img src="images/gplus.png" alt="plus button" /> buttons. This bookmarklet makes it easy to plus-one any page directly while browsing it - share from anywhere!</p>

<p>To install the bookmarklet just drag the <code>Google+1</code> link below to your browser bookmarks bar:</p>

<div style="text-align:center;font-size:75px; font-family:'Ubuntu Mono',monospace;"><a href="javascript:var gpc=document.createElement('div');gpc.style.position='fixed';gpc.style.top='50px';gpc.style.right='50px';gpc.style.padding='50px';gpc.style.backgroundColor='#def';var gp=document.createElement('g:plusone');document.body.insertBefore(gpc,document.body.firstChild);gpc.appendChild(gp);window.___gcfg={lang:'en-GB'};(function(){var po=document.createElement('script');po.type='text/javascript';po.async=true;po.src='https://apis.google.com/js/plusone.js';var s=document.getElementsByTagName('script')[0];s.parentNode.insertBefore(po,s);})();">Google+1</a></div>

<p>To use the bookmarklet at any time while browsing the web just click the link on your bookmarks bar and a +1 button will appear in the top-right corner of the page. Click the plus one button to share and comment just like you would on any other site that already has +1 buttons (feel free to test it out on this page!).</p>

<p>I have tested this bookmarklet in Chrome 16.0.9 and Firefox 8.0. Please leave a comment if you have trouble with other browsers and I'll see what I can do.</p>

<p>Internet Explorer 6 users might struggle - the bookmarklet code is longer than IE6 can cope with. May I suggest upgrading to one of the many much better browsers available, such as <a href="http://www.google.com/chrome">Chrome</a> or <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/new/">Firefox</a>. </p>

<p>Alternatively you can try this bookmarklet (disclaimer: I cannot test it - I don't have IE6) - drag the "Google+1" to your browser links bar:</p>

<div style="text-align:center;margin:auto;font-size:75px; font-family:'Ubuntu Mono',monospace;"><a href="javascript:var gpc=document.createElement('div');gpc.style.position='fixed';gpc.style.top='50px';gpc.style.right='50px';var gp=document.createElement('g:plusone');document.body.insertBefore(gpc,document.body.firstChild);gpc.appendChild(gp);window.___gcfg={lang:'en-GB'};(function(){var po=document.createElement('script');po.type='text/javascript';po.async=true;po.src='https://apis.google.com/js/plusone.js';var s=document.getElementsByTagName('script')[0];s.parentNode.insertBefore(po,s);})();">Google+1</a>(IE6)</div>

<p>Enjoy!</p>
]]></description>
          <category>google+</category>
          <category>g+</category>
          <category>+1</category>
          <category>plusone</category>
          <category>bookmarklet</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Pointing a domain name to an Amazon S3 bucket]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/pointing_a_domain_name_to_an_amazon_s3_bucket.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/pointing_a_domain_name_to_an_amazon_s3_bucket.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>I recently registered a domain name for some static content i'm hosting in Amazon's Simple Storage Service (S3). <a href="hosting_a_static_website_in_amazon_s3.html">Setting up an S3 bucket as a static website</a> is pretty straight-forward, but pointing your domain to it is tricky. After a bit of playing and googling I think I've got the right combination:</p>

<h4>Step-1: Create your S3 website bucket</h4>

<p>When naming your bucket you <em>must</em> use the same name as your domain - e.g. <code>www.mydomain.com</code>. The website end-point will then be something like <code>www.mydomain.com.s3-website-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com</code>. If you don't do this you will get warnings (404 not found, nosuchbucket).</p>

<h4>Step-2: Remove any existing "A" records</h4>

<p>Using the administration tools provided by your domain registrar, remove any <code>"A"</code> records that may have been automatically set up for your domain - you don't want your domain name pointing to "parking" sites.</p>

<h4>Step-3: Forward your root domain to www</h4>

<p>Forward your root domain (<code>mydomain.com</code>) to the <code>www</code> subdomain (<code>www.mydomain.com</code>). Most registrars and hosting companies give you the ability to forward domain names. With Fasthosts I had to "add" forwarding to my package, but it didn't cost anything extra.</p>

<p>If you can <em>mask</em> the forwarding, so much the better, as this will mean that visitors to your site will see your registered domain rather than the S3 url (depends what your registrar offers - fasthosts and godaddy both support masked forwarding). In Fasthosts admin, masking is a checkbox option in the forwarding configuration.</p>

<h4>Step-4: Add a `CNAME` pointing to your S3 site</h4>

<p>Add a CNAME for the <code>www</code> subdomain, pointing to your S3 website (<code>www.mydomain.com.s3-website-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com</code>). The admin tools should make this easy for you.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-6aH7JLLgpVQ/TtFmqVjl4QI/AAAAAAAAH0k/vT_wK-8EEd0/s522/cname-config.png" alt="Add a CNAME" /></p>

<p>That's it - all you have to do now is wait for the changes to propagate (this can take a while).</p>

<h4>See it in action...</h4>

<p>You can see this in action with my setup:</p>

<p>My domain-name is overpayment-calculator.com, which forwards to <a href="http://www.overpayment-calculator.com">www.overpayment-calculator.com</a>, which points (via CNAME) at my S3 bucket <a href="http://www.overpayment-calculator.com.s3-website-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com">www.overpayment-calculator.com.s3-website-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com</a>, masking the S3 name (so that when you visit via the overpayment-calculator.com address you don't see the S3 address in the address bar).</p>

<p><em>p.s.</em> props to <a href="http://www.fasthosts.co.uk/">fasthosts</a> - the dns information propagated extremely quickly - from registering the domain name to acessing my site via that domain name (including the time it took me to do the set up) took less than one hour!</p>
]]></description>
          <category>Amazon</category>
          <category>S3</category>
          <category>domain name</category>
          <category>forward</category>
          <category>mask</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Microformats, rich snippets, rel=author, and search listings]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/microformats_rich_snippets_rel_author_and_search_listings.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/microformats_rich_snippets_rel_author_and_search_listings.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Whilst moving my blog from Blogger to github pages I've been looking into various ways to bump up my traffic. </p>

<p>I came across <a href="http://schema.org">schema.org</a> microformats some time ago and read about plans from Google, Yahoo and Microsoft to support them. I implemented the <a href="http://schema.org/BlogPosting">BlogPosting</a> microformat to mark up my posts "semantically", and waited to see what google would make of it.</p>

<p>I admit, I was pretty excited at the thought of my search listings being presented in a more interesting fashion - I think that would really make them stand out. Here's an example of what Google's "rich snippets" testing tool makes of my articles:</p>

<p><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-svXxV_v3GEM/Ts7iHUCNneI/AAAAAAAAHyY/lpTiC3ZKFI0/s867/rich-snippets.png" alt="rich snippets info for one of my blog posts" /></p>

<p>Unfortunately to-date it hasn't made a great deal of difference to how my posts are presented in a google search result.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-56_YwrdGwv4/Ts7VbPtTwHI/AAAAAAAAHw8/s__A_feIMnY/s600/search-listing.png" alt="google search listing" /></p>

<p>The first result in that listing image is for my blog. The only difference I see is that my blog result shows a date (which is nice, but I'm not sure its there because of the rich snippets markup - my old blogger blog shows dates like this too, and currently has no metadata markup that I can spot in the html source).</p>

<p>So much for rich snippets. </p>

<p>More recently I came across <code>rel=author</code>, and again I've been quite excited to try it out. This time I checked before-hand and found a handful of webby types who've got this working on their blogs. Here's what they look like:</p>

<p><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-j1PTvhmppyU/Ts7XnanwE-I/AAAAAAAAHxs/N4Z7toDlRN0/s600/rel-author-search-listing.png" alt="google search listing with rel=author" /></p>

<p>A couple of weeks later I'm still having a bit of a trial getting this to work. I've done the setup exactly as described by google and a bunch of these other guys who've got it working - no joy. I'm using the three-way setup as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li>From each blog post, link to my about page with rel="author" (I've linked the lego man image at top-right in the header).</li>
<li>From my about page, link to my google profile with rel="me" (I have two links, one <code>&lt;link rel="me"&gt;</code> in the <code>&lt;head&gt;</code>, and one in an <code>&lt;a rel="me" ..</code> in the G+ icon in the navigation bar just below the header.</li>
<li>From my google profile, create a contributes-to link back to my about page.</li>
</ul>

<p>The reason for this set of reciprocal links is so that google can trust that the content really is produced by you, and its no hard-ship to set up. Except that for some reason I can't fathom it just <em>doesn't work for me</em>.</p>

<p>The rich-snippets testing tool gives me the all-clear, and even shows an example search listing:</p>

<p><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-DKGP9ZJF8G0/Ts7aVKcwJiI/AAAAAAAAHyE/ZHCauxKCvYM/s600/rich-snippets-search-listing.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>I've tried about a dozen variants now, each time waiting for a re-index before trying something different (you can tell when you've been indexed using Google's <a href="http://www.google.com/webmasters/tools/">Webmaster Tools</a>).</p>

<p>So far I've tried:</p>

<ul>
<li>Relative links between blog-post and about page</li>
<li>Absolute links between blog-post and about page</li>
<li>All links as <code>&lt;link&gt;</code> elements in the <code>&lt;head&gt;</code></li>
<li>All links as <code>&lt;a&gt;</code> elements in the page <code>&lt;body&gt;</code></li>
<li>All combinations of the above alternatives</li>
</ul>

<p>I have a few remaining alternatives in the works. One is to remove all rel=me links to profiles other than google (I currently also have twitter and linked-in profiles linked with rel=me). </p>

<p>Another is to add a link to my google+ profile in an <code>&lt;a href="https://plus.google.com/105248011271585565954?rel=author"&gt;Steve+&lt;/a&gt;</code> (yes, with the + at the end of the link text - see <a href="http://www.google.com/support/webmasters/bin/answer.py?answer=1408986">option 2, here</a>). </p>

<p>There's also <a href="https://spreadsheets.google.com/spreadsheet/viewform?formkey=dHdCLVRwcTlvOWFKQXhNbEgtbE10QVE6MQ">this form</a> which sounds tantalisingly like it might be a necessary part of the process, and which I hadn't previously seen mentioned anywhere. I've submitted the form, but a bit of googling suggests that it will make no difference.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>rel=author</category>
          <category>rich snippets</category>
          <category>microformats</category>
          <category>schema.org</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[A multi-class union CSS selector]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/a_multi_class_union_css_selector.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/a_multi_class_union_css_selector.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p><style> <br />
  .urgent { color:red; }
  .important { font-weight:bold; }
  .urgent.important { font-style:italic; }
</style>
Several times while working on the styling of this blog I've wanted to style elements differently when the complete combination or set union of css classes are used on the same element. If the css classes are applied separately the style should not apply. Until today I didn't realise that this is, in fact, both possible and easy to achieve.</p>

<p>Here's the html I want to be able to write:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;div class="urgent"&gt;something urgent&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="important"&gt;something important&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="urgent important"&gt;urgent &amp; important&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>And this is how that should look:</p>

<div class="example">
  <div class="urgent">something urgent</div>
  <div class="important">something important</div>
  <div class="urgent important">urgent & important</div>
</div>

<p>The urgent &amp; important text should be bold, red and italic in your browser. Notice that neither the "urgent" or the "important" are italic - that only comes when both css classes combine on the same element.</p>

<p>Here are three ways you can achieve the effect. Make sure you get to option-3, even if you have to skip options 1 and 2 (hint: they both suck).</p>

<h3>Option 1: specific, separate css class</h3>

<pre><code>&lt;style&gt;
  .urgent { color:red; }
  .important { font-weight:bold; }
  .both   { font-style:italic; }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class="urgent"&gt;Red Text&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="important"&gt;Bold Red Text&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="urgent important both"&gt;Bold Italic Red Text&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>This is nasty. I want to define my css classes to be as orthogonal and meaningful as possible, and while creating my html markup I do not want to be "mixing concerns" that should be kept separate.</p>

<h3>Option 2: nested html tags and ancestry selectors</h3>

<pre><code>&lt;style&gt;
  .urgent { color:red; }
  .important { font-weight:bold; }
  .urgent .important { font-style:italic }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class="urgent"&gt;Red Text&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="important"&gt;Bold Red Text&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="urgent"&gt;
  &lt;div class="important"&gt;Bold Italic Red Text&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Double nasty, take it away! Now I've had to change my html markup to nest <code>.important</code> under <code>.urgent</code>, just so I can style things as I want them. It also doesn't work if I nest them the other way around. This is really stupid and annoying: styling should be separate from markup.</p>

<p>OK, so here's the right way to do it, and I just can't believe it took me so long to feel the pain hard enough to go looking for a solution...</p>

<h3>Option 3: use the union selector</h3>

<pre><code>&lt;style&gt;
  .urgent { color:red; }
  .important { font-weight:bold; }
  .urgent.important { font-style:italic; }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class="urgent"&gt;Red Text&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="important"&gt;Bold Text&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="urgent important"&gt;Bold Italic Red Text&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>The difference in the css declaration between option-2 and option-3 is so small I'll point it out, just in case you missed it: </p>

<ul>
<li>the union selector uses <em>both</em> class names <em>without</em> the space separating them - like this <code>.urgent.important</code>.</li>
<li>whereas the example in option-2 <code>.urgent .important</code> separates the two classes with a space, and matches on an element with <code>.important</code> descending from an element with <code>.urgent</code>.</li>
</ul>

<p>CSS can be a thumping great pain, but just occasionally it comes up trumps.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>css</category>
          <category>selector</category>
          <category>union</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Weighted Average smoothing with Java2d]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/weighted_average_smoothing_with_java2d.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/weighted_average_smoothing_with_java2d.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Since my <a href="">original post</a> I've done a little bit more playing with processing images to try to give them a "vectorised" look. I really didn't change much, just played with the algorithm for choosing pixel colour. The algorithms all work by examining the colours of the current and surrounding pixels to determine what colour to paint the current pixel. The colour selection is performed by classes that implement the following simple interface:   </p>

<pre><code>interface Counter {
    // add a colour channel value for one of 
    // the neighbouring pixels
    public void add(int aValue);

    // calculates the value we should use
    // for the current colour channel of the
    // current pixel based on its neighbours
    public int mostFrequent();
}
</code></pre>

<p>The client code that deals this interface invokes the add method 3 times for each pixel - once for each colour channel (red / green /blue). The client code looks like this:</p>

<pre><code>// calculate the colour 
private int count(int anOffset, int[] aSurrounding) {
    Counter _c = getCounter();
    int _length = aSurrounding.length-(2-anOffset);
    for (int i=anOffset; i&amp;lt;_length; i+=3) {
        _c.add(aSurrounding[i]);
    }
    return _c.mostFrequent();
}
</code></pre>

<p>Here you can see that I can easily supply different implementations of Counter, so I can try different algorithms easily.</p>

<h3>The original colour-selection algorithm</h3>

<p>The original algorithm simply takes the most frequent value of each colour channel so that, for example, if 51% of the surrounding pixels are bright blue, and the other 49% are bright red, this pixel will be bright red.</p>

<pre><code>class SimpleCounter implements Counter {
    int[] values = new int[256];

    public SimpleCounter() {
        Arrays.fill(values, -1);
    }

    public void add(int aValue) {
        values[aValue] += 1;
    }

    public int mostFrequent() {
        int _highest = -1;
        int _colour = -1;
        for (int i=0; i&amp;lt;256; i++) {
            if (values[i] &amp;gt; _highest) {
            _highest = values[i];
            _colour = i;
            }
        }
        return _colour;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>This algorithm does produce the effect I'm looking for, but I get some sharp edges and colour bleeding that I don't really want (see example output below).</p>

<h3>The weighted-average algorithm</h3>

<p>This algorithm weights the values of the surrounding pixels relative to the most common value, so we get a weighted average that does take some account of less popular colours in the neighbourhood of the current pixel.</p>

<pre><code>class WeightedAverageCounter implements Counter {
    int[] values = new int[256];

    public WeightedAverageCounter() {
        Arrays.fill(values, 0);
    }

    public void add(int aValue) {
        values[aValue] += 1;
    }

    public int mostFrequent() {
        int _max = max();
        double _weight=0, _colour=0, _count=0;
        for (int i=0; i&amp;lt;256; i++) {
            if (values[i] &gt; 0) {
                _weight = (((double)values[i]) / _max);
                _weight = Math.pow(_weight, 5);
                _colour += _weight * i;
                _count += _weight;
            }
        }
        return (int) (_colour / _count);
    }

    private int max() {
        int _highest = 0;
        for (int i=0; i&amp;lt;256; i++) {
            if (values[i] &gt; _highest) {
                _highest = values[i];
            }
        }
        return _highest;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The result of the weighted average algorithm is a much smoother colour composition with a reduction in the aliasing effects that can be seen in the more simple algorithm's output. It does have a significant performance penalty however - on my quad core i7 laptop on an image of 600x650 pixels and a 16x16 neighbourhood, the simple algorithm completes in 10 seconds, whereas the weighted-average needs 90 seconds!</p>

<h3>Output for comparison</h3>

<p>Here are some examples for comparison. First is the original image, then then the image processed with the simple colour selection algorithm, followed by the weighted average algorithm.</p>

<p><img alt="The original photograph" width="600" height="654" src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-zPwUf1ZwEes/TsfLHPhDT0I/AAAAAAAAHuI/Rpt4as1QyIE/s600/duck.jpg"></p>

<div class="caption">The original image</div>

<p><img alt="Processed with 'Simple' algorithm" width="600" height="654" src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/--uqph05DLD4/TsfLMt4MJ3I/AAAAAAAAHuU/aJ_bXBLOFEw/s600/duck-16x16-simple.png"></p>

<div class="caption">Processed with 'Simple' algorithm</div>

<p><img alt="Processed with 'Weighted Average' algorithm" width="600" height="654" src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-C6hRgaQDTtA/TsfLRfOMKLI/AAAAAAAAHuc/gLLTePCCUfo/s600/duck-16x16-weighted-average.png"></p>

<div class="caption">Processed with 'Weighted Average' algorithm</div>

<p>It might be a little difficult to see the difference, so here's one final composite image showing the difference close-up and side-by-side</p>

<p><img alt="composite - left-side 'simple', right-side 'weighted average'" width="600" height="327" src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-i6hEeV2vdC0/TsfYihtEPaI/AAAAAAAAHu8/Yx2b4FTSvBM/s600/duck-composite.jpg"></p>

<div class="caption">Composite for comparison</div>

<p>The left-side shows the image processed with the simple algorithm, whilst the right-side shows the smoother result of the weighted-average algorithm.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>Image</category>
          <category>Processing</category>
          <category>Java2D</category>
          <category>Convolve</category>
          <category>Kernel</category>
          <category>Vectorize</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Mortgage/Loan Overpayment Calculator]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/mortgage_loan_overpayment_calculator.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/mortgage_loan_overpayment_calculator.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks back I was talking with someone who was looking into over-paying a loan. The premise is that, provided your lender allows overpayments, by over-paying you can save a fortune in interest payments.</p>

<p>The amount you can save isn't all that straight-forward to work out, due to the miracle that is compound interest. I knocked up a quick <a href="http://www.overpayment-calculator.com/">overpayment calculator</a> using <code>gwt.progressive</code>, which I'm <a href="hosting_a_static_website_in_amazon_s3.html">hosting at Amazon S3</a> with a <a href="pointing_a_domain_name_to_an_amazon_s3_bucket.html">registered domain name</a>.</p>

<p>Here's one of the classes that's being bound - or "activated" if you like - by gwt.progressive:</p>

<pre><code>public class OverpaymentSummary extends Composite {
    interface MyActivator extends WidgetActivator&amp;lt;OverpaymentSummary&gt;{}
    MyActivator activator = GWT.create(MyActivator.class);

    @RuntimeUiWidget(id="saving") InlineLabel saving;
    @RuntimeUiWidget(id="years") InlineLabel years;
    @RuntimeUiWidget(id="months") InlineLabel months;

    public OverpaymentSummary(Element anElement) {
        initWidget(activator.activate(this, anElement));
    }

    public void setResults(
        Money aStandardTotal, int aStandardMonths, 
        Money anOverpaidTotal, int anOverMonths) {
        saving.setText(aStandardTotal.minus(anOverpaidTotal).toString());

        int _monthsSaved = aStandardMonths - anOverMonths;
        setYears(_monthsSaved/12);
        setMonths(_monthsSaved - ((_monthsSaved/12)*12));

        removeStyleName("hidden");
    }

    private void setYears(int aYears) {
        years.setText(""+aYears);
    }

    private void setMonths(int aMonths) {
        months.setText(""+aMonths);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Which is bound onto html that looks like this:</p>

<pre><code>&amp;lt;div class="summary hidden"&gt;By overpaying you could save
&amp;lt;span id="saving"&gt;???&amp;lt;/span&gt;, and reduce your mortgage 
term by &amp;lt;span id="years"&gt;?&amp;lt;/span&gt; years and 
&amp;lt;span id="months"&gt;?&amp;lt;/span&gt; months!&amp;lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Notice the <code>&amp;lt;span&gt;</code> elements with the id's "saving", "years", and "months" - these are bound automatically to the three <code>InlineLabel</code>'s annotated with <code>@RuntimeUiWidget</code>.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>Mortgage</category>
          <category>Loan</category>
          <category>Overpayment</category>
          <category>Calculator</category>
          <category>GWT</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Creating a "Vectorisation" effect with Java2D]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/creating_a_vectorisation_effect_with_java2d.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/creating_a_vectorisation_effect_with_java2d.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>On my <a href="http://steveliles.github.com/about_me.html">about me</a> page I have a picture of myself wearing a stupid hat and an even more stupid grin. This picture started out as an old photograph from which I removed the background using GIMP, then vectorized using an online tool called <a href="http://vectormagic.com/home">Vector Magic</a>.</p>

<p>Vector Magic is a very cool tool - it converts bitmap's to vector images by "tracing" the bitmap. Once vectorised you can rescale the image as large as you like without losing the smooth edges.</p>

<p>Here are the two images of me - on the left is the bitmap (before vectorisation) and on the right is a bitmap of the vectorized image created by Vector Magic (I vectorised the image for the comic-book <em>effect</em> of vectorisation, not in order to use the vector image itself):</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <td><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-TW1qOjU0mxY/TsQyq8NZ8mI/AAAAAAAAHpw/o2s_M3fUDNk/s291/before.png"></td>
    <td><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-okVBiU07UVo/TsQyq2py0HI/AAAAAAAAHps/Wk7l-acfBxY/s281/after.png""></td>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>Hopefully you can see the effect I'm talking about - large areas of colour are blocked out, and generally you get a kind of comic-book or oil-painting effect.</p>

<p>After vectorizing that image I started wondering how it worked and if I could whip up something myself, and so I began playing with Java2D to see if I could get close.</p>

<h2>"Hatching" the image</h2>

<p>I began my efforts with a very simple approach of testing pixels in each row and "dragging" a pixel colour across adjacent pixels until I encounter a pixel with a significantly different colour, at which point I swap the current colour and repeat the process.</p>

<p>Thanks to Java2D doing all the heavy lifting, the code is pretty short:</p>

<pre><code>public void hatch() {
    // load the image and extract the raster data
    BufferedImage _img = loadImage("cat.jpg");
    Raster _raster = _img.getData();

    // prepare a new raster to write the hatched
    // version of the image to
    BufferedImage _copy = new BufferedImage(
        _img.getWidth(), _img.getHeight(), _img.getType());
    WritableRaster _writable = _copy.getRaster();

    double[] _current = new double[3];
    double[] _previous = new double[3];
    double[] _write = new double[3];

    int _threshold = 75;

    for (int y=0; y&amp;lt;_img.getHeight(); y++) {
        for (int x=0; x&amp;lt;_img.getWidth(); x++) {
            // for each pixel in the image, decide whether
            // to use its original colour, or to drag in the
            // colour of a preceding pixel
            _current = _raster.getPixel(x, y, _current);
            _write = decide(_previous, _current, _threshold);
            _writable.setPixel(x, y, _write);
            _previous = Arrays.copyOf(_write, _write.length);
        }
    }

    // save the result to a new png file
    ImageIO.write(_copy, "png", new File("cross-hatch.png"));
}

private double[] decide(double[] aThis, double[] aThat, int aThreshold) {
    for (int i=0; i&amp;lt;aThis.length; i++) {
        if (Math.abs(aThis[i] - aThat[i]) &amp;gt; aThreshold) {
            return aThat;
        }
    }
    return aThis;
}
</code></pre>

<p>This has an interesting arty effect of "hatching" the image, but before the vectorisation effect becomes significant I start to get colour runs, where the colour gets dragged too far. </p>

<p>I played around with combining vertical and horizontal (and even diagonal) hatching with lower thresholds, which again produces a nice arty effect - particularly on hi-res images, but it isn't really the effect i'm looking for.</p>

<p>Below are some (lo-res) examples, using a high threshold value to make the effect more pronounced.</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-WaE9HVjyP00/TsQ5Mnf749I/AAAAAAAAHqY/QhN9JEmDW8o/s290/cat.jpg"><div class="caption">original image</div></th>
    <th><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-TMtXRSp3G68/TsQ5QdqoajI/AAAAAAAAHqg/7axdHs9O34I/s290/vertical.png"><div class="caption">vertical hatching</div></th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <th><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-iwdfREXJWx8/TsQ5o1FhKXI/AAAAAAAAHqo/MsgbftSuYs4/s290/horizontal.png"><div class="caption">horizontal hatching</div></th>
    <th><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-nsB6SodNjCg/TsQ6A0HMeJI/AAAAAAAAHq8/KPhxcJyPEQ4/s290/cross-hatch.png"><div class="caption">cross hatching</div></th>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>If you look carefully at certain areas of the images you can see the colour runs - for example on the dark area just where the cats leg joins its body at bottom right of the image, you can see the lighter brown vertical lines in the vertical-hatching image, and similar horizontal lines in the horizontal hatching image.</p>

<p>Notice that the cross-hatching image is starting to get the blocky effect somewhat similar to vectorisation, but pushing the thresholds high enough to create significant blocks of colour ruins the overall effect by dragging too much colour across the image.</p>

<p>I tried various techniques to reduce the drag effect - including an inverse-square factor of the distance since the colour was first encountered. This did indeed smooth things quite a bit, but still doesn't achieve the effect i'm looking for. Time for a new approach.</p>

<h2>Edge Detection</h2>

<p>Next I pondered some obvious techniques like edge detection. The classic mechanism for edge detection is to apply a filter, or convolution kernel, where each pixel is treated with respect to several surrounding pixels. Simple edge detection kernels look something like this:</p>

<table style="width:auto; margin:auto;">
  <tr>
    <th>
      <table style="width:90px; border:1px solid black; margin:20px;">
        <tr>
      <th class="caption">-1</th>
      <th class="caption">0</th>
      <th class="caption">1</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <th class="caption">-2</th>
      <th class="caption">0</th>
      <th class="caption">2</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <th class="caption">1</th>
      <th class="caption">0</th>
      <th class="caption">1</th>
    </tr>
      </table>
      <div class="caption">Horizontal</div>
    </th>
    <th>
      <table style="width:90px; border:1px solid black; margin:20px;">
        <tr>
      <th class="caption">-1</th>
      <th class="caption">-2</th>
      <th class="caption">-1</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <th class="caption">0</th>
      <th class="caption">0</th>
      <th class="caption">0</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <th class="caption">1</th>
      <th class="caption">2</th>
      <th class="caption">1</th>
    </tr>
      </table>
      <div class="caption">Vertical</div>
    </th>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>Here's what running the "horizontal" edge-detection kernel on the cat image produces:</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>
      <img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-ISL5K81GcKQ/TsRF_VK5KYI/AAAAAAAAHrY/xov4o7PQkMQ/s290/horiz-edge.png">
      <div class="caption">Edge Detected</div>
    </th>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>And the code for that, again made very simple by Java2D's built in convolution support:</p>

<pre><code>public void edgeDetect() throws Exception {
    BufferedImage _input = loadImage("cat.jpg");
    BufferedImage _horiz = convolve(_input, newHorizontalKernel());
    ImageIO.write(_horiz, "png", new File("edge.png"));
}

private BufferedImage convolve(BufferedImage anImage, Kernel aKernel) {
    BufferedImage _out = new BufferedImage(
        anImage.getWidth(), anImage.getHeight(), anImage.getType());

    ConvolveOp _op = new ConvolveOp(aKernel, ConvolveOp.EDGE_NO_OP, null);
    _op.filter(anImage, _out);

    return _out;
}

private Kernel newHorizontalKernel() {
    return new Kernel(3, 3, new float[] {
        -2, -4, -2,
        0, 0, 0,
        2, 4, 2
    });
}

private Kernel newVerticalKernel() {
    return new Kernel(3, 3, new float[] {
        -2, 0, 2,
        -4, 0, 4,
        -2, 0, 2
    });
}
</code></pre>

<p>This is a neat result, and probably I could use the edges thus detected as indicators of where to switch colours, but this just seems like a very round-about way of producing what i want. Time for a new approach.</p>

<h2>Convolution with a dynamic kernel</h2>

<p>After scratching my head for a while I figured that what I really want to do is somewhere between the two approaches outlined above. I want to use a weighted function of the surrounding pixels (like a convolution kernel), but I want to do something a bit more complex than I can achieve with a static convolution kernel.</p>

<p>After quite a bit more monkeying around I finally nailed it. This time I'm examining pixels around the current one, finding the most common value for each colour channel, and giving the current pixel the most common value for each colour channel. Strictly speaking this isn't a convolution operation at all, but the analogy is a useful one.</p>

<p>I get some slightly funky alias effects on some images, so my next task is to smooth that out, but overall the results are very close to what I was after.</p>

<p>Here's the code:</p>

<pre><code>public void vectorEffect()
throws Exception
{
    BufferedImage _img = loadImage("cat.jpg");
    Raster _raster = _img.getData();

    BufferedImage _copy = new BufferedImage(
        _img.getWidth(), _img.getHeight(), _img.getType());
    WritableRaster _writable = _copy.getRaster();

    int _blockWidth = 8;
    int _blockHeight = 8;

    int _halfWidth = _blockWidth / 2;
    int _halfHeight = _blockWidth / 2;

    int[] _lens = new int[(_blockWidth * _blockHeight) * 3];

    for (int y=0; y&amp;lt;_img.getHeight(); y++) {
        for (int x=0; x&amp;lt;_img.getWidth(); x++) {
            // get the surround NxM pixel grid as a
            // one dimensional array of r,g,b values
            _lens = _raster.getPixels(
                Math.max(0, x-_halfWidth), 
                Math.max(0, y-_halfHeight), 
                Math.min(_img.getWidth()-x, _blockWidth), 
                Math.min(_img.getHeight()-y, _blockHeight), 
                _lens
            );
            _writable.setPixel(x, y, getPixelColour(_lens));
        }
    }

    ImageIO.write(_copy, "png", new File("vector-effect.png"));
}

// choose the colour for the current pixel by finding the most
// common value for each colour channel in the surrounding pixels
private int[] getPixelColour(int[] aSurrounding) {
    int[] _result = new int[3];
    _result[0] = mostFrequent(0, aSurrounding);
    _result[1] = mostFrequent(1, aSurrounding);
    _result[2] = mostFrequent(2, aSurrounding);
    return _result;
}

// find the most frequent colour level for a given channel
// within the surrounding pixels. offset of 0 gives red channel,
// 1 gives green channel, 2 is blue channel
private int mostFrequent(int anOffset, int[] aSurrounding) {
    Counter _c = new Counter();
    int _length = aSurrounding.length-(2-anOffset);
    for (int i=anOffset; i&amp;lt;_length; i+=3) {
        _c.add(aSurrounding[i]);
    }
    return _c.mostFrequent();
}

// relatively efficient counter for quickly racking up 
// a count of occurrences of any given colour level
class Counter {
    int[] values = new int[256];

    public Counter() {
        Arrays.fill(values, -1);
    }

    public void add(int aValue) {
        values[aValue] += 1;
    }

    public int mostFrequent() {
        int _highest = -1;
        int _colour = -1;
        for (int i=0; i&amp;lt;256; i++) {
            if (values[i] &amp;gt; _highest) {
                _highest = values[i];
                _colour = i;
            }
        }
        return _colour;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>And here's what the resulting "vector-effect" image looks like:</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>
      <img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-h7WklR032Mk/TsRN6coQ38I/AAAAAAAAHsQ/JWkuc8ANBY0/s290/vector-effect.png">
      <div class="caption">4x4 sample grid</div>
    </th>
    <th>
      <img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-vsw4wvURlK4/TsRJkaFlyBI/AAAAAAAAHr0/B8JSW3ZA7yQ/s290/vector-effect.png">
      <div class="caption">8x8 sample grid</div>
    </th>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>Because of the low resolution of this image, a large grid size quickly reduces the resultant image quality. On larger images (e.g. 8MP photos) a 16x16 or even 32x32 grid produces good results. The time to render is proportional to the grid size though.</p>

<h2>Me Again</h2>

<p>Here's the results of processing my viking-hat picture with four different grid sizes: 2x2, 4x4, 8x8 and 16x16. You can see that at such a low resolution the image quickly degenerates with a large grid size - I'm looking pretty demonic by the time we get to 16x16:</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-NuogXfqNWmA/TsRU2sshuKI/AAAAAAAAHtM/ikSxFtH3i9w/s291/after-2x2.png"><div class="caption">2x2</div></th>
    <th><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-hE6Z_o9mrR4/TsRU2ohWggI/AAAAAAAAHtQ/cTkyx-gYM9I/s291/after-4x4.png"><div class="caption">4x4</div></th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <th><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-w37U7iH5tfg/TsRU2qiVWXI/AAAAAAAAHtI/0Id8prE6AZ4/s291/after-8x8.png"><div class="caption">8x8</div></th>
    <th><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-ZViGZb-uaIA/TsRVE7M2jRI/AAAAAAAAHts/3yFJbGNleX4/s291/after-16x16.png"><div class="caption">16x16</div></th>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2>A High-Resolution Image</h2>

<p>An 8MP image (3456x2304) processed with a 16x16 grid takes about 50 seconds on my quad-core i7 laptop. The same image processed with an 8x8 grid takes 27 seconds.</p>

<p>This last image was processed at its full size (3456x2304) with a 16x16 grid, then the result was cropped and resized (by more than 50%) in GIMP to fit the width of my blog.</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>
      <img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-JiE1KHRC6qs/TsRPaJYe7OI/AAAAAAAAHss/kYIP-Llk-0k/s600/vector-16x16.png">
      <div class="caption">vector effect, using a 16x16 grid</div>
    </th>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2>What's next?</h2>

<p>Well its still some way off from the clean look that Vector Magic produces, but I think its a good start. I'm going to try some ideas to de-fuzz and clean up the edges a bit.</p>

<p>After that ... I'm wondering if I can take the next step and identify bounds for the areas of colour, and thus create a vector image from my "vector-effect" bitmaps?</p>
]]></description>
          <category>Image</category>
          <category>Processing</category>
          <category>Java2D</category>
          <category>Convolve</category>
          <category>Kernel</category>
          <category>Vectorize</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Syntax Highlighting with GWT.Progressive]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/syntax_highlighting_with_gwt_progressive.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/syntax_highlighting_with_gwt_progressive.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>There are many good syntax-highlighters available for progressively enhancing code on website's such as my blog. On my old blog I used <a href="http://alexgorbatchev.com/SyntaxHighlighter/">Alex Gorbachev's</a> - which is exceptionally good.</p>

<p>For this blog, I really wanted to write my own. Why? Well, for the same reason I wrote the site-generation software that builds the blog from Markdown templates - because I love programming, and doing this stuff is FUN!</p>

<p>Having just released my <code>GWT.Progressive</code> library I had two very good reasons to write a syntax-highlighter that works by progressive-enhancement:</p>

<ol>
<li>I need good examples of progressive enhancement written in <code>GWT</code> using <code>GWT.Progressive</code></li>
<li>Those very same code-samples need syntax-highlighting to aid readability!</li>
</ol>

<p>For this first attempt I'm not setting out to write the world's greatest syntax-highlighter. My aims are more modest: merely to illustrate the <code>GWT.Progressive</code> library and add basic syntax-highlighting (Java) capabilities to my blog.</p>

<p>The syntax-highlighter will work as follows:</p>

<ol>
<li>After the page is loaded, identify <code>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; ... &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</code> blocks on my blog.</li>
<li>Try to ascertain if the text in the block is Java, or a similar language (e.g. JavaScript).</li>
<li>Mark keywords, literals, comments, and a few other choice elements using inline html markup to add css classes, allowing the actual colours and styles to be selected independently of the process of identify the parts to highlight.</li>
</ol>

<p>The script that kicks this off is loaded by the very last line in the html body of each page on my blog:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;script 
  type="text/javascript" language="javascript" 
  src="blog/blog.nocache.js"&gt;
&lt;/script&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>The Java class that uses the <code>GWT.Progressive</code> library to scan for <code>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;</code> blocks is, in full, as follows:</p>

<pre><code>package com.sjl.blog.client.syntax;

import com.google.gwt.core.client.*;
import com.google.gwt.dom.client.*;
import com.knowledgeview.gwt.activator.client.*;
import com.knowledgeview.gwt.activator.client.widgets.*;

@RootBinding(tag="code")
public class Code extends BoundRootPanel {
    interface MyActivator extends ElementActivator&lt;Code&gt;{}
    static MyActivator activator = GWT.create(MyActivator.class);

    static JavaSyntaxHighlighter highlighter = 
        new JavaSyntaxHighlighter();

    public Code(Element anElement) {
        setElement(activator.activate(this, anElement));

        if (isJavaCode(getElement().getInnerText())) {
            getElement().setInnerHTML(
                highlighter.highlight(getElement().getInnerText()));
        }
    }

    private boolean isJavaCode(String aString) {
        return !aString.trim().startsWith("&lt;");
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>GWT</code> module descriptor looks like this:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;module rename-to="blog"&gt;
  &lt;inherits name="com.google.gwt.user.User"/&gt;
  &lt;inherits name="com.google.gwt.user.Debug"/&gt;

  &lt;inherits name="com.sjl.gwt.progressive.Progressive"/&gt;
  &lt;entry-point class="com.sjl.blog.client.BlogApplication" /&gt;

      &lt;!-- allows the script to be used cross domain --&gt;
  &lt;add-linker name="xs" /&gt;
&lt;/module&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>I will take the time to write a better highlighter some time in the future (using ANTLR or similar to generate a parser), but for now I knocked up a simple version using regular expressions.</p>

<p>This highlighter was built by TDD'ing my way through highlighting the different components, starting simple with keywords. The design changed a few times along the way, but in total, including the <code>Code</code> class, the finished highlighter took around 90 minutes to build.</p>

<p>The slowest part, actually, was round-trip testing and fixing "for real" with GWT production mode, since the <a href="http://google-web-toolkit.googlecode.com/svn/javadoc/2.4/com/google/gwt/regexp/shared/RegExp.html">difference in regular expression engines</a> between development and production mode caught me out.</p>

<p>Here's the Java syntax highlighter in full:</p>

<pre><code>public class JavaSyntaxHighlighter implements SyntaxHighlighter {
    private List&amp;lt;Replacement&gt; replacements;

    public JavaSyntaxHighlighter() {
        replacements = new ArrayList&amp;lt;Replacement&gt;();

        // order is important
        replacements.add(new CommentReplacement());
        replacements.add(new AnnotationReplacement());
        replacements.add(new LiteralReplacement());
        replacements.add(new KeywordReplacement());
    }

    public String highlight(String anInput) {
        List&amp;lt;Component&gt; _components = new ArrayList&amp;lt;Component&gt;();
        _components.add(new SplittableComponent(anInput));

        for (Replacement _r : replacements) {
        _components = _r.process(_components);
        }

        StringBuilder _sb = new StringBuilder();
        for (Component _c : _components) {
        _sb.append(_c);
        }
        return _sb.toString();
    }
}

interface Component {
    boolean canSplit();
    String toString();
}

class SplittableComponent implements Component {
    protected String value;

    public SplittableComponent(String aValue) {
        value = aValue;
    }

    public boolean canSplit() {
        return true;
    }

    public String toString() {
        return value;
    }
}

class UnsplittableComponent extends SplittableComponent {
    public UnsplittableComponent(String aValue) {
        super(aValue);
    }

    public boolean canSplit() {
        return false;
    }
}

interface Replacement {
    public List&amp;lt;Component&gt; process(List&amp;lt;Component&gt; anInput);
}

abstract class AbstractReplacement implements Replacement {
    private String cssClass;

    public AbstractReplacement(String aCssClass) {
        cssClass = aCssClass;
    }

    protected abstract String replace(String aString);

    @Override
    public List&amp;lt;Component&gt; process(List&amp;lt;Component&gt; aComponents)
    {
        List&amp;lt;Component&gt; _result = new ArrayList&amp;lt;Component&gt;();
        for (Component _c : aComponents) {
        if (_c.canSplit()) {
            String _replaced = replace(_c.toString());
            _result.addAll(createComponents(_replaced, cssClass));
        } else {
            _result.add(_c);
        }
        }
        return _result;
    }

    private List&amp;lt;Component&gt; createComponents(
        String anInput, String aClass) {
        List&amp;lt;Component&gt; _result = new ArrayList&amp;lt;Component&gt;();
        for (String _s : anInput.split("\\[\\[\\[|\\]\\]\\]")) {
        if (_s.startsWith("&amp;lt;span class=\"" + aClass)) {
            _result.add(new UnsplittableComponent(_s));
        } else {
            _result.add(new SplittableComponent(_s));
        }
        }
        return _result;
    }

    protected String replacement(String aClass) {
        return "[ [ [&amp;lt;span class=\"" + aClass + "\"&amp;gt;$1&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;] ] ]";
    }
}

class KeywordReplacement extends AbstractReplacement
{
    public static String[] KEYWORDS = new String[] {
        "class", "package", "import", "public", "private", "protected", 
        "interface", "extends", "this", "implements", "throws", "try", 
        "catch", "finally", "final", "return", "new", "void", "for", 
        "if", "else", "while", "static", "transient", "synchronized", 
        "byte", "short", "int ", "char ", "long ", "float ", "double ", 
        "boolean ", "true", "false", "abstract", "volatile", "switch", 
        "case"
    };

    public KeywordReplacement() {
        super("sh-keyword");
    }

    protected String replace(String aString) {
        String _result = aString;
        for (String _k : KEYWORDS) {
        _result = _result.replaceAll("(" + _k + ")", 
                replacement("sh-keyword"));
        }
        return _result;
    }
}

class LiteralReplacement extends AbstractReplacement {

    public LiteralReplacement() {
        super("sh-literal");
    }

    protected String replace(String aString) {
        return aString.replaceAll("(\"[^\"]*\")", 
            replacement("sh-literal"));
    }
}

class CommentReplacement extends AbstractReplacement {
    public CommentReplacement() {
        super("sh-comment");
    }

    protected String replace(String aString) {
        String _result = aString.replaceAll("(//.*)", 
            replacement("sh-comment"));
        _result = _result.replaceAll("(\\/\\*[\\*]?.*\\*\\/)", 
            replacement("sh-comment"));
        return _result;
    }
}

class AnnotationReplacement extends AbstractReplacement {
    public AnnotationReplacement() {
        super("sh-annotation");
    }

    protected String replace(String aString) {
        return aString.replaceAll("(@\\w+)", 
            replacement("sh-annotation"));
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>You can find out more about <code>GWT.Progressive</code> in the <a href="gwt_progressive.html">release announcement</a>, or at the <a href="https://github.com/steveliles/gwt-progressive">github repository</a>.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>syntax</category>
          <category>highlight</category>
          <category>java</category>
          <category>GWT</category>
          <category>progressive</category>
          <category>enhancement</category>
          <category>regexp</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[gwt.progressive]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/gwt_progressive.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/gwt_progressive.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<h2>Easy Progressive-Enhancement with GWT</h2>

<p>Progressive-enhancement is a technique for delivering a basic website suitable for search-engines and older web-browsers, then layering on polish, effects, interactivity and general goodness using javascript - the idea being to have a graceful degradation of service, not an all-or-nothing experience.</p>

<p>Traditionally <code>GWT</code> works the other way around - it builds all of the <code>DOM</code> structure of your web-app in script, so search-engines (and browsers with script disabled) only see an inscrutable mass of script.</p>

<p><code>GWT.Progressive</code> helps to bring your ninja <code>GWT</code> skills to bear on web-sites that need progressive enhancement.</p>

<p>You can get <code>GWT.Progressive</code> from the <a href="https://github.com/steveliles/gwt-progressive">git repository</a> at github.</p>

<h2>What can GWT.Progressive do for me?</h2>

<ul>
<li>Bind <code>GWT</code> widgets to html elements on static (or server-generated) html pages, using the html as a template and <code>GWT</code> magic to "enhance" the user-experience</li>
<li>Automatically bind nested html elements to properties of widget classes (child widgets, grand-child widgets, etc)</li>
<li>Bind repeated html elements to <code>List&lt;MyWidgetClass&gt;</code> properties of widget classes</li>
<li>Automatically bind attributes of html elements to properties of widget classes - with automatic type coercion</li>
<li>Make partial page-updates a breeze (replacing parts of the <code>DOM</code> with new server-generated content)</li>
</ul>

<h2>How GWT.Progressive works</h2>

<h3>Element Binding</h3>

<p>You can bind a <code>GWT</code> widget to any html element on your website - just by adding an annotation to the widget class:</p>

<pre><code>// bind by id
@RootBinding(id="mywidget")
class MyWidget extends Composite {
    //...
}

// bind by tag name
@RootBinding(tag="h1")
class MyWidget extends Composite {
   //...
}

// bind by css class
@RootBinding(cssClass="bind-me")
class MyWidget extends Composite {
   //...
}

// bind by tag name and css class
@RootBinding(tag="div", cssClass="bind-me")
class MyWidget extends Composite {
   //...
}
</code></pre>

<p>Bind nested html to child widgets:</p>

<pre><code>// bind the first &amp;lt;h1&gt; tag we find by breadth first
// search of the DOM within our widget's root element
@RuntimeUiWidget(tag="h1") MyHeaderWidget header;

// bind the first element we find by breadth first
// search that has the css class "foo"
@RuntimeUiWidget(cssClass="foo") MyFooWidget foo;
</code></pre>

<p>Bind repeated elements to a List of child widgets:</p>

<pre><code>// bind all the &amp;lt;img&gt; elements we find inside our
// widget's root element to the list of Image widgets
@RuntimeUiWidget(tag="img") List&lt;Image&gt; images;
</code></pre>

<h3>Attribute Binding</h3>

<p>Bind html attributes as properties of your widgets, with automatic type coercion:</p>

<pre><code>// the following attributes will have their default values (set below)
// overridden by the values of attributes in the html, if they exist
@RuntimeUiAttribute("text-attr") String textAttr = "default";
@RuntimeUiAttribute("int-attr") Integer integerAttr = 22;
@RuntimeUiAttribute("long-attr") Long longAttr = 9L;
@RuntimeUiAttribute("float-attr") Float floatAttr = 2.3f;
@RuntimeUiAttribute("double-attr") Double doubleAttr = 2222222.222d;
@RuntimeUiAttribute("boolean-attr") Boolean booleanAttr = false;
</code></pre>

<p>Bind attributes to custom types by supplying converters - given html like: <code>&lt;div coords="200x400"&gt; ... &lt;/div&gt;</code>, automatically bind the coords property of our widget as an instance of Coords, converted by CoordsAttributeConverter...</p>

<p>In the <code>Widget</code> we're binding:</p>

<pre><code>// automatically bind our custom Coords class 
@RuntimeUiAttribute("coords") Coords coords;
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>Coords</code> class:</p>

<pre><code>class Coords {
    public Integer x, y;
    public Coords(Integer anX, Integer aY) {
        x = anX;
        y = aY;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>AttributeConverter</code>:</p>

<pre><code>@RuntimeUiAttributeConverter
public class CoordsAttributeConverter 
extends AttributeConverter&lt;Coords&gt; {
    public Coords convert(String aString) {
        String[] _parts = aString.split("x");
        return new Coords(
            Integer.parseInt(_parts[0]), 
            Integer.parseInt(_parts[1])
        );
    }
}
</code></pre>

<h3>Partial Page Updates</h3>

<p>Replace chunks of html with new html from the server. Your server can provide this html as it pleases - for example you can call servlets, jsp's, PHP or whatever you like to get the html for the replacement. Your widgets will re-bind to the new html after adding it to the <code>DOM</code>.</p>

<pre><code>// UiBinder afficionados will be familiar with this plumbing
// which we'll use to invoke our page update...
interface MyActivator extends ElementActivator&lt;Partial&gt;{}
MyActivator activator = GWT.create(MyActivator.class);

// here's the widget we're going to update
@RuntimeUiWidget(tag="div") UpdateMe updateMe;

    ...

// call this method to trigger the update
private void someMethod() {
    activator.update(
        updateMe, "/update-me.jsp", 
        new CallMeWhenUpdated()
    );
}
</code></pre>

<h3>Partial Page Update callbacks</h3>

<p>You can register callbacks to trigger when a partial update completes - successfully or otherwise. Here's a more complete partial update example:</p>

<pre><code>@RootBinding(tag="div")
public class Partial extends BoundRootPanel
    // UiBinder afficionados will be familiar with this
    interface MyActivator extends ElementActivator&lt;Partial&gt;{}
    MyActivator activator = GWT.create(MyActivator.class);

    @RuntimeUiWidget(tag="div") UpdateMe updateMe;

    public Partial(Element anElement)
    {
        setElement(activator.activate(this, anElement));

        // Update the page when we're clicked...
        addDomHandler(new ClickHandler() {
            public void onClick(ClickEvent aEvent) {
                activator.update(
                    Partial.this, "/update-me.jsp", 
                    new CallMeWhenUpdated()
                );
            });
        }            
    }, ClickEvent.getType());

    class CallMeWhenUpdated 
    implements PageUpdateCallback&lt;Partial&gt;() {
        public void onSuccess(Partial anUpdated) {
            Window.alert("Updated!");
        }

        public void onError(Throwable anExc) {
            GWT.log("oops, something bad happened", anExc);
        }   
    }
}
</code></pre>

<h3>Complete example - Progressive Enhancement with GWT</h3>

<p>Here's the HTML we're going to enhance:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;div class="widget"&gt;
      &lt;img class="first" src="/image-1.png"&gt;
      &lt;img class="second" src="/image-2.png"&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;!-- our script loads last, and progressive 
         enhancement begins --&gt;
    &lt;script 
        type="text/javascript" language="javascript" 
        src="example/example.nocache.js?cache=20111112180652"&gt;
    &lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Here's the widget we're going to bind to the <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> of css-class "widget":</p>

<pre><code>@RootBinding(cssClass="widget")
class MyWidget extends BoundRootPanel {
    interface MyActivator extends ElementActivator&lt;MyWidget&gt;{}
    MyActivator activator = GWT.create(MyWidget.class);

    @RuntimeUiWidget(cssClass="first") Image first;
    @RuntimeUiWidget(cssClass="second") Image second;

    public MyWidget(Element anElement) {
        setElement(activator.activate(this, anElement);

        // ... now we do some enhancements, e.g. add
        // click-handlers to our image's or something
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>We'll need an EntryPoint - this is still a <code>GWT</code> application:</p>

<pre><code>class Example1 implements EntryPoint {
    public void onModuleLoad() {
        PageActivator _activator = GWT.create(PageActivator.class);
        _activator.activate();
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>... and a <code>GWT</code> module descriptor (<code>.gwt.xml</code>) of course:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;module rename-to="example"&gt;
  &lt;inherits name="com.google.gwt.user.User"/&gt;
  &lt;inherits name="com.sjl.gwt.progressive.Progressive"/&gt;

  &lt;entry-point class="com.sjl.example.client.Example" /&gt;

  &lt;!-- for maximum compatibility, use the xs linker --&gt;
  &lt;add-linker name="xs" /&gt;
&lt;/module&gt;
</code></pre>

<h2>Rules of engagement</h2>

<p><code>GWT.Progressive</code> requires that you follow a few simple rules to ensure that your widgets get "activated" correctly, integrated into the GWT/browser eventing system, etc.</p>

<p>Your widgets <em>must</em>:</p>

<ul>
<li>Have a public <code>Constructor</code> that takes a <code>com.google.gwt.dom.client.Element</code> argument, OR</li>
<li>Have a <code>public static &lt;T&gt; wrap(Element anElement)</code> method that returns an instance of your widget class (this is how native GWT widgets like Image and Label are bound by GWT.Progressive).</li>
<li><code>GWT.create()</code> a special class that allows <code>GWT.Progressive</code>'s generator to work its magic on your widgets (either <code>com.sjl.gwt.progressive.client.ElementActivator</code> or <code>com.sjl.gwt.progressive.client.WidgetActivator</code>).</li>
<li>Set your Widget's Element as the return value from activation (<code>setElement(activator.activate(this, anElement))</code>) or init your Composite with it (<code>initWidget(activator.activate(this, anElement))</code>).</li>
</ul>

<p>If you've ever used UiBinder, this pattern will be very familiar to you.</p>

<p>Also, make sure to use the "xs" linker by specifying <code>&lt;add-linker name="xs"/&gt;</code> in your gwt module descriptor for maximum compatibility.</p>

<h3>Where can I find more examples of GWT.progressive?</h3>

<p>In the github repository, in the <a href="https://github.com/steveliles/gwt-progressive/tree/master/src/java/test/com/sjl/gwt/progressive">test source tree</a>.</p>

<h3>Are there any examples in the wild?</h3>

<p>There are two examples on this page! - The Twitter feed in the sidebar, and the code <a href="syntax_highlighting_with_gwt_progressive.html">syntax-highlighting</a> are both implemented using <code>gwt.progressive</code>.</p>

<p>You can also try my mortgage/loan <a href="http://www.overpayment-calculator.com/">overpayment calculator</a> which is built with gwt.progressive.</p>

<h3>Can I use this in my products?</h3>

<p>Sure, its available under the Apache-2.0 license, and is a github fork away, but ... disclaimer: use at your own risk and discretion, I cannot accept responsibility for any issues that may arise from using this library.</p>

<h3>Can I modify the code, fix bugs, etc?</h3>

<p>Knock yourself out :) ... I'd love to hear about it if you do.</p>

<h2>Final Words</h2>

<p>I just want to say - props to my employer (<a href="http://www.knowledgeview.com">KnowledgeView ltd.</a>) for allowing me to release the code, some of which was developed on their dime. Mucho thanks KV :)</p>

<p>You can find some more background on <code>GWT.Progressive</code> in some of my earlier blog posts: <a href="http://steveliles.github.com/progressive_enhancement_with_gwt_part_1.html">part-1</a>, <a href="http://steveliles.github.com/progressive_enhancement_with_gwt_part_2.html">part-2</a>, and <a href="http://steveliles.github.com/progressive_enhancement_with_gwt_part_3.html">part-3</a></p>
]]></description>
          <category>GWT</category>
          <category>Progressive</category>
          <category>Enhancement</category>
          <category>Library</category>
          <category>Apache2</category>
          <category>SEO</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Templating my Blog with FreeMarker]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/templating_my_blog_with_freemarker.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/templating_my_blog_with_freemarker.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Part of the fun of shifting my Blog from Blogger to github has been building the static-site-generator tool which reads my blog content as <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax">Markdown</a> and spits it out as html + css.</p>

<p>I'm using <a href="http://code.google.com/p/markdownj/">MarkdownJ</a> to convert the Markdown syntax to HTML, and <a href="http://freemarker.sourceforge.net/">FreeMarker</a> for templating.</p>

<p>FreeMarker for templating was an easy choice for me:</p>

<ul>
<li>It is a decent templating engine that I've used recently for a dynamic website,</li>
<li>It is very easy to set up in Java for my one-hit templating needs,</li>
<li>I like its syntax compared to, say, Velocity</li>
</ul>

<p>Yesterday I used FreeMarker to add two new productions to my site-generator: a sitemap, and an RSS feed, and thought I'd make some quick notes...</p>

<p>FreeMarker strives to be a pure templating language, and as such resists the temptation to ... shall we say, make certain things easy that you probably shouldn't do in a template. </p>

<p>This can make templating a little uncomfortable sometimes - all the more so if you try to use complex domain objects directly in your templates instead of producing model's specifically for output (YMMV depending on the complexity of your domain model of course).</p>

<p>For the simple needs of my Blog FreeMarker has been great, allowing me to whiz up the sitemap template in a couple of minutes, and not much longer for the RSS-2.0 template.</p>

<p>Setting up FreeMarker in Java is very very simple indeed. I chose to abstract FreeMarker away behind my own interface (<code>TemplateProcessor</code>), in case I want to use something different later:</p>

<pre><code>import java.io.*;
import freemarker.template.*;

public class FreemarkerTemplateProcessor implements TemplateProcessor
{
    private Configuration cfg;

    public FreemarkerTemplateProcessor(File aTemplateDir) 
    throws IOException
    {
        cfg = new Configuration();
        cfg.setDirectoryForTemplateLoading(aTemplateDir);
        cfg.setObjectWrapper(new DefaultObjectWrapper());
    }

    @Override
    public void process(Object aModel, String aTemplate, Writer aWriter) 
    throws IOException, TemplateException
    {
        Template _tpl = cfg.getTemplate(aTemplate);
        _tpl.process(aModel, aWriter);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The templating language is quite neat, and very easy to write - as I mentioned before, it helps if your model is a good fit for the view you are trying to render so you don't need to squeeze to many conditionals into the template. </p>

<h2>Freemarker template for sitemap.xml</h2>

<p>There are only 3 lines of FreeMarker markup in my sitemap template:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>&lt;#list posts as post&gt;</code> which iterates over an <code>Iterable</code> containing <code>Post</code> objects,</li>
<li>the closing <code>&lt;/#list&gt;</code>, and</li>
<li>the line that reads the post's link <code>&lt;loc&gt;${blog.url}/${post.link}&lt;/loc&gt;</code></li>
</ul>

<p>Here's the template in full:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt; 
&lt;urlset xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation=
        "http://www.sitemaps.org/schemas/sitemap/0.9 
        http://www.sitemaps.org/schemas/sitemap/0.9/sitemap.xsd"
  xmlns="http://www.sitemaps.org/schemas/sitemap/0.9"&gt; 

  &lt;url&gt;
    &lt;loc&gt;${blog.url}/index.html&lt;/loc&gt;
    &lt;changefreq&gt;daily&lt;/changefreq&gt;
    &lt;priority&gt;1.0&lt;/priority&gt;
  &lt;/url&gt;
  &lt;url&gt;
    &lt;loc&gt;${blog.url}/about_me.html&lt;/loc&gt;
    &lt;changefreq&gt;daily&lt;/changefreq&gt;
    &lt;priority&gt;0.9&lt;/priority&gt;
  &lt;/url&gt;

  &lt;#list posts as post&gt;
    &lt;url&gt; 
      &lt;loc&gt;${blog.url}/${post.link}&lt;/loc&gt;
      &lt;changefreq&gt;hourly&lt;/changefreq&gt;
    &lt;/url&gt;
  &lt;/#list&gt;

&lt;/urlset&gt;
</code></pre>

<h2>Freemarker template for RSS 2.0</h2>

<p>The RSS template is very similar to the sitemap template, as it deals with exactly the same model. Skipping the pre-amble, here's the part that actually involves any freemarker markup:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;#list posts as post&gt;
  &lt;item&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;&lt;![CDATA[${post.title}]]&gt;&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;link&gt;&lt;![CDATA[http://${blog.url}/${post.link}]]&gt;&lt;/link&gt;
    &lt;guid isPermaLink="true"&gt;${blog.url}/${post.link}&lt;/guid&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;&lt;![CDATA[${post.body}]]&gt;&lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;#list post.keywords as keyword&gt;
      &lt;category&gt;${keyword}&lt;/category&gt;
    &lt;/#list&gt;
    &lt;dc:creator&gt;&lt;![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]&gt;&lt;/dc:creator&gt;
    &lt;pubDate&gt;${post.date?string("EEE, dd MMM yyyy HH:mm:ss Z")}&lt;/pubDate&gt;
  &lt;/item&gt;
&lt;/#list&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>I like the date built-in here: <code>${post.date?string("EEE, dd MMM yyyy HH:mm:ss Z")}</code> which keeps the date format in the template where it belongs. </p>

<p>Of course, here I've just written it directly into this template because I only use this format once in my whole site - if I were using it more I could define a re-usable FreeMarker macro instead to avoid repetition.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>FreeMarker</category>
          <category>Template</category>
          <category>Sitemap</category>
          <category>RSS</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Most geeky thing I ever saw]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/most_geeky_thing_i_ever_saw.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/most_geeky_thing_i_ever_saw.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>There's something fabulously, deliciously geeky about using Curl to call a url-shortening service for url's to the web-management console of an online source-code-control system! <a href="http://git.io/help">Githubber's you ROCK!</a></p>

<p><code>curl -i http://git.io -F "url=https://github.com/blog/985-git-io-github-url-shortener" -F "code=geek"</code></p>

<p>gives:</p>

<pre><code>HTTP/1.1 201 Created
Server: nginx/1.0.4
X-Node: gitio2
X-Sha: 50f8f21981a362dfbaa5fbc85193621e56379dfb
Content-Type: text/html;charset=utf-8
Date: Thu, 10 Nov 2011 23:23:12 GMT
Status: 201 Created
Location: http://git.io/help
X-Runtime: 0.008420
Connection: keep-alive
Content-Length: 0
</code></pre>
]]></description>
          <category>github</category>
          <category>geek</category>
          <category>url-shortener</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[ Popularity contest - Ubuntu vs OSX Lion vs Win7]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/popularity_contest_ubuntu_vs_osx_lion_vs_win7.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/popularity_contest_ubuntu_vs_osx_lion_vs_win7.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>A while back I played with Google Trends to compare <a href="linux_distro_popularity.html">Linux distribution popularity</a>. Ubuntu was the clear winner.</p>

<p>In that post I also tried to compare OSX and Windows7 against the Linux supremo, but I think I didn't hit on the right search term for OSX.</p>

<p>I tried again today out of curiosity, and I think I got better results, though perhaps still not really reflecting the true state of the world (I'm <em>sure</em> OSX kicks Ubuntu's pants in reality).</p>

<p><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-Dzc_zxe0T1c/Trw6VrnoVgI/AAAAAAAAHo4/wA3dBag5IFw/s900/ubuntu-vs-lion-vs-win7-2011-11-10.png" alt="ubuntu(blue), windows7(red), OSX Lion(orange)" /></p>

<p><code>ubuntu(blue), windows7(red), OSX Lion(orange)</code></p>

<p>More at <a href="http://www.google.com/trends?q=ubuntu%2C+windows+7%2C+lion&amp;ctab=0&amp;geo=all&amp;date=all&amp;sort=0">Google Trends</a>.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>Linux</category>
          <category>Ubuntu</category>
          <category>OSX Lion</category>
          <category>Windows7</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Eclipse code template for GWT jsni methods]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/eclipse_code_template_for_gwt_jsni_methods.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/eclipse_code_template_for_gwt_jsni_methods.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>GWT JavaScriptObject's and JavaScript Overlays are very cool. I've written about them <a href="gwt_javascriptobjects_javascript_overlays.html">before</a>. It can get a bit tiresome to write jsni methods though, especially all those fiddly slashes, braces and asterisks at the end!</p>

<p>Here's a simple Eclipse code template that does the hard work for you, and lets you quickly tab-and-type through to completing your jsni method without ever having to type those fiddles again:</p>

<pre><code>public final native ${return_type} ${newName}()/*-{ 
    ${cursor} 
}-*/;
</code></pre>

<p>To add this in Eclipse:</p>

<ol>
<li>Open the preferences dialog (Window -> Preferences)</li>
<li>Type "templates" into the filter box (it should have focus already so you can just start typing)</li>
<li>Select the bold entry under "Java -> Editor -> Templates"</li>
<li>In the right hand panel you'll see all the existing templates, and some buttons ... Click "New"</li>
<li>The "name" is also the shortcut for your new template, so enter "jsni"</li>
<li>Paste in the template text (copy from the code block above).</li>
<li>Click ok to return to prefs, and ok again to return to the editor and try it out ...</li>
</ol>

<p>To use your new template:</p>

<ol>
<li>Type "jsni" (without quotes) into a java editor and hit ctrl-space (or whatever your auto-complete shortcut is)</li>
<li>The first option in the auto-complete suggestions should be your "jsni" template - hit return to use it</li>
<li>Your template appears, and eclipse focuses the first part (the return type) for you to modify</li>
<li>Modify each part of the template in turn and press tab to move to the next part</li>
<li>Enjoy!</li>
</ol>

<p>Recent releases of the Google Eclipse plugin include some <a href="http://code.google.com/eclipse/docs/gwt_jsni.html">nice jsni features</a> that you definitely don't want to miss out on - including code-completion and syntax highlighting.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>eclipse</category>
          <category>code</category>
          <category>template</category>
          <category>jsni</category>
          <category>gwt</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[What makes a good developer?]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/what_makes_a_good_developer.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/what_makes_a_good_developer.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>At the beginning of the year I worked with our Operations Manager in Beirut - <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/pub/bassel-beaini/26/553/291">Bassel Beaini</a> - to do annual reviews for our whole development (and UX) team there. </p>

<p>As part of the review process we gave the developers an updated job specification, which I wanted to be both prescriptive and aspirational - the idea being to describe the role each should currently be playing, to make very clear what would be needed to move to the next level, and at the same time to make everyone want to up their game and take it to the next level.</p>

<p>The end result, I guess, is my attempt at a technology agnostic description of what makes a good developer. Being a developer myself I'm fairly biased towards the technical aspects of the role and probably tend to somewhat overlook the human side of things (team-work, interaction with other parts of the business incl. non-programmers, etc). I'd love to hear constructive feedback on how I could improve these descriptions for next year :)</p>

<p>Here are the "aspirational" parts of the job descriptions I wrote for the top-tiers - architect/expert and senior developer:</p>

<h2>Architect/Expert Developer</h2>

<p>A passionate technologist, you demonstrate excitement, deep interest and knowledge of all aspects of development: languages; paradigms; patterns; idioms; platforms; performance; reliability; scalability; quality; tools and technologies. You relish the challenge of hugely complex problems.</p>

<p>Possessing true mastery of at least one modern programming language and paradigm, along with advanced knowledge of idioms and Design Patterns and when (or when not) to apply them, you will be able to recognize opportunities to improve code at a glance, and have the confidence and competence to take these opportunities to refactor towards better design.</p>

<p>You must be able to explain at length the reasons behind (micro)architectural decisions you make - or help others to make - so that others may learn from you. Your code has a finesse and indescribable quality that is the envy of all who read and work with it. You have exceptional ability to narrow down potential sources of a problem, hone in on the root-cause, and propose a range of solutions and explain their pros and cons.</p>

<p>Your architectural skills allow you both to describe designs at a high level to the business, and also to hone in on the complexities and details that allow a design to be implemented successfully. You are able to interpret and translate abstract ideas from more business oriented colleagues and customers, and from those ideas produce designs and specifications for developers to implement. You will be able to identify and separate the real requirements from the incidental details that inevitably form part of such brain-storming or business driven interaction.</p>

<p>You will have excellent understanding and wider knowledge of development tools and processes, and be able to clearly explain, demonstrate, and teach their usage to others, especially those junior to yourself who may have no prior experience. You will be aware of facets of these tools and processes that are not in daily use, such that you will be able to turn these tools even more to your advantage in specific situations. You will be constantly looking for new ways to streamline your working practices and those of the team through use of new and existing tools and technologies.</p>

<p>As one of the most senior members of the development team you will set an excellent example of engineering discipline to your colleagues, and will be passionate about achieving the very best quality and helping those around you to do so. You will recognize and evangelize the benefits of engineering disciplines such as source-code control, unit-testing, and code-review, and have a very self-critical view of what constitutes "done".</p>

<p>You will delight in tackling a range of tasks, recognizing the pleasure to be found in a polished solution to the smallest problem, as well as the challenges of a more significant undertaking, and you will enjoy mentoring and engaging in discussion about all aspects of development with your colleagues.</p>

<h2>Senior Developer</h2>

<p>You are the kind of person who develops software for fun in your spare time - whether personal projects or open-source contributions. You are deeply interested in languages, paradigms, idioms, tools and technologies, and in solving difficult problems.</p>

<p>You take great pride in your work, and it shows clearly in the way your code speaks to others - simple, clean, thoroughly unit-tested and easily understood and maintained. You are able to recognize and fix many code-smells and can gently point them out to your less experienced colleagues during code-review. You are keen to develop your skills further through interaction with your colleagues - junior and senior - and by consistently executing any task, large or small, with the attitude that there is always something new to learn. You can quickly identify and fix problems from minimal descriptions.</p>

<p>You are accomplished at taking high level designs and specifications from Architects and implementing them successfully, including creating and assigning suitable sub-tasks to less advanced members of your team. You can articulately explain the reasons behind micro-architectural choices you make during implementation, and evaluate the pros and cons of such decisions.</p>

<p>You will have excellent understanding and wider knowledge of development tools and processes, and be able to clearly explain, demonstrate, and teach their usage to others, especially those junior to yourself who may have little or no prior experience. You will be so confident with and reliant upon these tools that you use them even for your personal projects, knowing that the benefits are well worth the extra up-front effort.</p>

<p>You will set an excellent example of engineering discipline to your peers and junior colleagues, and you understand and truly believe in the need for engineering discipline and processes in delivering high quality software. Your attitude toward any task is to produce the best solution you can and learn from the experience. You will actively seek feedback on your solutions from peers and senior colleagues, whether by code-review or less formal discussion.</p>

<p>If you're in Beirut, are a serious Java or Objective-C hacker, and would like to work with us, drop a comment, contact <a href="http://uk.linkedin.com/in/steveliles">me</a> or <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/pub/bassel-beaini/26/553/291">Bassel</a> via linked-in, or tweet me (<a href="http://twitter.com/#!/steveliles">@steveliles</a>)</p>
]]></description>
          <category>Developer</category>
          <category>Architect</category>
          <category>Engineer</category>
          <category>Qualities</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[GWT JavaScriptObjects (Javascript Overlays)]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/gwt_javascriptobjects_javascript_overlays.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/gwt_javascriptobjects_javascript_overlays.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>GWT has a fantastic tool for "overlaying" java (GWT) classes on JSON objects such that you don't have to write any parsing code to parse a piece of JSON. There are some nice articles about this from the GWT folks themselves, for example <a href="http://code.google.com/webtoolkit/doc/latest/DevGuideCodingBasicsOverlay.html">this one</a>. The gist of it is, given some JSON like this:</p>

<pre><code>{ "item": {
    "id": 123,
    "name": "cheese",
    "type": "food"
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>we can "overlay" a java class onto that JSON, and have the GWT compiler (and the browser's native JSON parsing) do the marshalling for us. </p>

<h2>JavaScript Overlay Types</h2>

<p>We do that by writing a JavaScript Overlay Type class that maps the native json data back to the the world of your Java code, and looks like this:</p>

<pre><code>public class Item extends JavaScriptObject
{
    protected Item(){}

    public final native Integer getId()/*-{ 
        return this.id; 
    }-*/;

    public final native String getName()/*-{ 
        return this.name; 
    }-*/;

    public final native String getType()/*-{ 
        return this.id; 
    }-*/;
}
</code></pre>

<h2>JSNI Methods</h2>

<p>Those three native methods are known in GWT-land as JSNI methods (JavaScript Native Interface), and the part in comments at the end is actually pure JavaScript that you can write to directly access parts of the JSON object. </p>

<p>In these native JSNI sections the "this" object being referred to is the JSON object itself, and although I've only shown very simple property access here you can in fact perform more complex operations if you like.</p>

<p>The return values from our JSNI can be Java's primitive wrappers or String, any class that extends JavaScriptObject (JSO), or one of a number of special JSO classes GWT provides such as JsArray, JsIterable, JsArrayString, etc.</p>

<p>I have exclusively used jsni methods in my example above, but you can include pure java methods as well (provided they are final) - say, for example, we need to parse a date from some json:</p>

<pre><code>public class Item extends JavaScriptObject
{
    private static final DateTimeFormat df = 
        DateTimeFormat.getFormat("yyyyMMdd");

    protected Item(){}

    public final Date whenCreated() {
        return df.parse(getCreateDateString());
    }

    public final native Integer getId()/*-{ 
        return this.id; 
    }-*/;

    public final native String getName()/*-{ 
        return this.name; 
    }-*/;

    public final native String getType()/*-{ 
        return this.id; 
    }-*/;

    public final native String getCreateDateString()/*-{ 
        return this.createDate; 
    }-*/;
}
</code></pre>

<h2>Mapping complex types</h2>

<p>These are simple examples of course, but i've had no trouble mapping even the most complex JSON objects using JSO's. You can map arrays easily enough using the built in GWT JsArray types, like this:</p>

<pre><code>public class Items extends JavaScriptObject
{
    protected Items(){}

    public final native JsArray getItems()/*-{ 
        return this.items; 
    }-*/;
}
</code></pre>

<p>Which would map the following JSON:</p>

<pre><code>{ items: [
  {
    "id": 123,
    "name": "cheese",
    "type": "food"
  },
  {
    "id": 456,
    "name": "ham",
    "type": "food"
  },
  {
    "id": 789,
    "name": "eggs",
    "type": "food"
  }]
}
</code></pre>

<h2>JavaScriptObject rules</h2>

<p>There are a couple of basic rules to follow:</p>

<ul>
<li>Must have a protected no-arg constructor</li>
<li><em>All</em> methods must be "final"</li>
<li>Must not have any instance fields</li>
<li>May only implement a single Interface</li>
</ul>

<h2>JavaScriptObject "gotchas"</h2>

<p>With regard to that last point, there's another gotcha to look out for: only one JavaScriptObject class can implement any given interface. Think about that for a minute, because its more of a restriction than you might at first realise...</p>

<p>The whole point of Interfaces is to use them to define a contract that implementations will adhere to, so that multiple poly-morphically interchangeable implementations can be used. With JSO's, you can only have one single JSO implementation of an interface - for example you cannot have several JSO's which implement Iterable. This is for the same reason that all JSO methods must be final - JSO's cannot use dynamic method dispatch.</p>

<p>If you try to implement the same interface in more than one of your JSO's you don't (currently) get any warnings from the compiler ... instead you get crazy runtime behaviour due to the wrong JSO class's methods being invoked (because one of your JSO's will receive all method invocations for the interface, regardless of which class the method should have been invoked against).</p>

<p>Interestingly I ran into a problem in the latest GWT release (2.4) that reported a very unhelpful error message (I'm sure the messages in earlier releases of GWT were much more helpful actually). Here's the error message I got:</p>

<pre><code>java.lang.ClassFormatError: Illegal method name "$"
 in class com/xxx/xxx/client/model/UserResult
 at java.lang.ClassLoader.defineClass1(Native Method)
 at java.lang.ClassLoader.defineClassCond(ClassLoader.java:631)
 at java.lang.ClassLoader.defineClass(ClassLoader.java:615)
 at java.lang.ClassLoader.defineClass(ClassLoader.java:465)
 at com.google.gwt.dev.shell.CompilingClassLoader.findClass
    (CompilingClassLoader.java:1085)
 at java.lang.ClassLoader.loadClass(ClassLoader.java:306)
 at java.lang.ClassLoader.loadClass(ClassLoader.java:247)
</code></pre>

<p>... as it turns out, the problem actually was that I broke one of the rules - I had a non-final method in my JavaScriptObject. Not a very helpful error message in this case, which is fairly unusual in my experience of GWT.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>GWT</category>
          <category>JavaScript</category>
          <category>Overlay</category>
          <category>JSO</category>
          <category>JSON</category>
          <category>Parsing</category>
          <category>JSNI</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[On 'Flow' and feeling productive]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/on_flow_and_feeling_productive.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/on_flow_and_feeling_productive.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>I like to feel productive. Actually that's a huge understatement. If I'm not feeling productive I get quite unhappy. For me feeling productive goes hand in hand with creative output - something that produces a tangible artifact - and I find it difficult to satisfy my need for productivity with intangible things like meetings.</p>

<p>Even more than that, I need to be deeply involved in the creative activity - part of the group doing the creative stuff rather than managing it from a distance.</p>

<p>This post has been brewing for a while, and I finally began composing it last week. At the weekend I ran out of Kindle-fodder and bought <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/ericries">@ericries</a> 's new book <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0670921602/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=stlibl-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0670921602">The Lean Startup</a>, and was amazed and pleased to hit upon the following quote, which said it all much better than I could: </p>

<table>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0670921602/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&tag=stlibl-21&linkCode=as2&camp=1634&creative=19450&creativeASIN=0670921602"><img src="http://ecx.images-amazon.com/images/I/51qNUVObwFL._SL500_AA300_.jpg"></a>
</td>
<td>
<blockquote>"When people are used to evaluating their productivity locally, they feel that a good day is one in which they did their job well all day.</blockquote>
<blockquote>When I worked as a programmer, that meant eight straight hours of programming without interruption. That was a good day.</blockquote>
<blockquote>In contrast, if I was interrupted with questions, process, or - heaven forbid - meetings, I felt bad. What did I really accomplish that day? Code and product features were tangible to me; I could see them, understand them, and show them off. Learning, by contrast, is frustratingly intangible."</blockquote>
-- Eric Ries, in The Lean Startup
</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>Now I agree with almost all of that quote, except for the last sentence where I think the word "learning" is in some ways not fitting. I think Eric meant to encompass questions, process, meetings, and many other things in "learning", in which case I'd agree with him, but there certain kinds of "learning" which I find very productive. </p>

<p>Recently I've been exploring some new avenues in my work - straying away from spending all day coding and venturing into developing product ideas. At first it felt very uncomfortable and I didn't feel at all productive. Lately though I'm coming around to it. </p>

<p>For me part of the way through has been to find ways to turn what I'm thinking and doing into tangible artifacts that require some creative effort to produce - for example: drawing UI wireframes, writing up meetings and brainstorming sessions, and developing ideas in essay form. </p>

<p>By committing &amp;ideas to disk I've started to feel productive again. Perhaps its just a safety blanket really, but it feels good, and the best bit is that with each new artifact, essay, description, and wireframe I can link to previous artifacts for reference, backup or explanation (all are available online in our basecamp account), and the conversation gets richer. </p>

<p><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-zYYLyGL6IF8/Tnuwx1j5bHI/AAAAAAAAHmU/ohE6yl1bFQU/s554/Screenshot-Portable%2BDevices%2BBusiness%2BUnit%2B%253E%2BEasy%2BPublish%253A%2Bassumptions%2Band%2Buse-cases%2B-%2BGoogle%2BChrome-1.png" alt="Basecamp Messages" /> </p>

<p>I've begun to wonder if some of my feeling of productivity actually comes from spending a certain amount of time each day in a state of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_(psychology">flow</a>), and if I don't get to spend some time each day in that state then I feel less happy and productive. </p>

<p>There are a few activities - mostly creative in some way - during which I find myself zoning out and really getting immersed in what i'm doing: coding; drawing; reading (novels); and - with a bit of effort - writing. Once i'm tuned out I can go on for hours without feeling time passing. </p>

<p>When I'm coding at home, with no distractions, I'll sit at the table in morning when my wife leaves for work and will hardly have moved by the time she comes home. I've noticed that I even realize, sometimes, that i'm in this state and have a "lucid flow" moment akin to lucid dreaming. Usually I get this when I hit a turning point in my work: when I've been working on a problem for a couple of hours and finally feel the complete shape of the solution in my head - I'm as deep into the problem as I'm going to get, I can start unwinding the mental stack, and from here on in progress is going to get quicker and quicker. Love that feeling. </p>

<table>
<tr>
<td>
<p>Coding is the creative activity that I spend most time on, so its also the activity that most often gets me into <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_(psychology))">flow</a>, but I find the most powerful activity for flow is drawing.</p>
<p>I suspect this has a lot to do with the difference between coding and drawing - the fact that coding requires the language centres of the brain to be active. Betty Edwards has quite a bit to say on this in Drawing on the Right Side of the Brain, which is an interesting read if you can draw reasonably well, but presumably a revelation if you've never been able to draw.</p>
</td>
<td>
<a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/images/0007116454/ref=dp_image_0?ie=UTF8&n=266239&s=books)"><img src="http://ecx.images-amazon.com/images/I/5114QGDGH7L._SL500_AA300_.jpg"></a>
</td>
</tr>
</table>
]]></description>
          <category>Flow</category>
          <category>Productivity</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[About Me]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/about_me.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/about_me.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>I didn't intend to have an about me page, but it turns out that to get google to display my mugshot next to search listings I have to have one. So here it is.</p>

<table>
<tr>
<td>
  <img src="images/viking.png">
</td>
<td>
  <img src="images/arrow-left.png">
</td>
<td>
  <p>This is me, the grinning idiot in the viking hat. Sadly I no longer have the hat.</p>
  <p>If you're interested, I took an (old) picture and vectorised it using <a href="http://vectormagic.com/">Vector Magic</a>, which allows online vectorising of a couple of images for free (thanks VectorMagic!)</p>
</td>
</tr>
</table>

<p>I graduated from Reading University with a BSc hons. degree in Computer Science and <a href="http://www.reading.ac.uk/cybernetics/">Cybernetics</a>, and immediately started work as a programmer at <a href="http://www.baesystems.com/">British Aerospace</a>, where I stayed for about a year and a half.</p>

<p>Next I moved on to work at a much smaller and more exciting company - <a href="http://www.knowledgeview.com">KnowledgeView</a> - where I have spent the last 11 years (oh me, oh my) developing a variety of web-based Editorial, Publishing and Syndication systems for news publishers - many based in the Middle-East and working and publishing in Arabic. We also build native and web apps for iPhone, iPad and Android devices to complement our publishing systems. </p>

<p>My current title is "Development Manager", though I think the job description would be better represented by the title "Chief Engineer". (A peculiar quirk of being a programmer is that you become a <a href="http://rcm-uk.amazon.co.uk/e/cm?lt1=_blank&amp;bc1=000000&amp;IS2=1&amp;bg1=FFFFFF&amp;fc1=000000&amp;lc1=0000FF&amp;t=stlibl-21&amp;o=2&amp;p=8&amp;l=as4&amp;m=amazon&amp;f=ifr&amp;ref=ss_til&amp;asins=B005LI3W9W]">pedant for nomenclature</a>). </p>

<p>I still code every day, for as many hours as I can. My "management style", if I have such a thing, is to lead by example. I care a lot about writing good code, using good tools, and leaving things in a better state than I found them. I try hard to <a href="what_makes_a_good_developer.html">enthuse my team</a> to the same ideals.</p>

<p>KnowledgeView is still small, though we have a growing team in Beirut. It's also occasionally quite exciting, otherwise I wouldn't still be there. Over the years we've had many high-profile customers, including:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.newsint.co.uk/">News International</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.cnnarabic.com">CNN arabic</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.inmplc.com/">Independent News and Media</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.srmg.com/en">Saudi Research and Media Group</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.daralhayat.com/">Al-Hayat Newspaper</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.alquds.co.uk/">Al-Quds</a></li>
<li>... and many more besides</li>
</ul>

<p>When I'm not at work I divide my time between growing veg on my allotment (conveniently just outside my garden gate) and working on my personal programming projects. </p>

<p>I believe that programming is the most fun a person can have on their own, and I often wonder if non-programmers know what they are missing out on. I sometimes find time to <a href="some_old_sketches.html">draw</a>, and wish I could find <a href="more_old_sketches.html">more</a>.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>steve liles</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[My first Android app (desktop widget)]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/my_first_android_app_desktop_widget.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/my_first_android_app_desktop_widget.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Having spent quite a bit of time away from Eclipse lately I've been itching to play with some code again. During a short meeting this morning an idea hit me for a really simple Android desktop widget: a twitter search widget that you can drop on your desktop and configure with a hash-tag search.</p>

<p>Here's how it looks in the Android emulator:</p>

<p><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-vquQDRX3D2Y/TmjCGIscAiI/AAAAAAAAHlw/g0nU2gdPnug/s815/tweet-widget.png" alt="Screenshot" /></p>

<p>I know, not exactly eye-candy, but that wasn't really the point :)</p>

<h3>The important pieces of the puzzle are:</h3>

<ul>
<li>A BroadcastReceiver that receives events telling the widget to update. Here I extended AppWidgetProvider to override onUpdate only.</li>
<li>A Service that does the Twitter API request asynchronously - we don't want to use the UI thread and fail the responsiveness criteria</li>
<li>The "widget info" descriptor xml</li>
<li>Android manifest entries that register the Service and the broadcast receiver</li>
<li>SAX ContentHandler implementation to parse the Tweet text from the atom response to the Twitter API request</li>
</ul>

<p>Here's the code, currently wired to display a search for "#uml"</p>

<h4>The BroadcastReceiver</h4>

<pre><code>public class NewsTicker extends AppWidgetProvider {
    @Override
    public void onUpdate(Context aContext, 
        AppWidgetManager aAppWidgetManager, 
        int[] aAppWidgetIds) {
        super.onUpdate(aContext, aAppWidgetManager, aAppWidgetIds);
        aContext.startService(
            new Intent(aContext, NewsTickerDataService.class));
    }
}
</code></pre>

<h4>The Service</h4>

<pre><code>public class NewsTickerDataService extends Service {

    @Override
    public void onStart(Intent aIntent, int aStartId) {
        super.onStart(aIntent, aStartId);   
        RemoteViews _views = buildUpdatedViews(this);   
        ComponentName _widget = 
            new ComponentName(this, NewsTicker.class);
        AppWidgetManager _manager = 
            AppWidgetManager.getInstance(this); 
        _manager.updateAppWidget(_widget, _views);
    }

    @Override
    public IBinder onBind(Intent aParamIntent) {
        // not supporting binding   
        return null;
    }

    private RemoteViews buildUpdatedViews(Context aContext) {
        List&amp;lt;Story&gt; _stories = getStories();
        RemoteViews _result = new RemoteViews(
            aContext.getPackageName(), 
            R.layout.newsticker_widget
        );

        if (_stories.isEmpty()) {
            _result.setTextViewText(R.id.title, 
                "Sadly there's nothing to read today.");
        } else {
            _result.setTextViewText(
                R.id.title, _stories.get(0).getTitle());
        }
        return _result;
    }

    private List&amp;lt;Story&gt; getStories() {
        try {
            URL _url = new URL("http://search.twitter.com" +
                "/search.atom?q=%23uml&amp;" + 
                "result_type=mixed&amp;count=5"
            );
            InputStream _in = _url.openStream();
            return parse(new InputSource(_in));
        } catch (Exception anExc) {
            Log.e("NewsTicker", anExc.getMessage(), anExc);
            return new ArrayList&amp;lt;Story&gt;();
        }
    }

    private List&amp;lt;Story&gt; parse(InputSource aSource)
    throws Exception {
        SAXParserFactory _f = SAXParserFactory.newInstance();
        SAXParser _p = _f.newSAXParser();
        XMLReader _r = _p.getXMLReader();

        AbstractParser _h = new AtomParser();
        _r.setContentHandler(_h);   
        _r.parse(aSource);

        return _h.getStories();
    }
}
</code></pre>

<h4>The SAX ContentHandler</h4>

<pre><code>public abstract class AbstractParser extends DefaultHandler {

    static interface Handler {
        Handler startElement(String aName);
        Handler characters(char[] aChars, int aStart, int aLength);
        Handler endElement(String aName);
    }

    public static AbstractParser newAtomParser() {
        return new AbstractParser() {
            protected String getStoryElementName() {
                return "entry";
            }
        };
    }

    private Handler handler;
    private List&amp;lt;Story&gt; stories;

    public AbstractParser() {
        stories = new ArrayList&amp;lt;Story&gt;();
        handler = newDefaultHandler();
    }

    protected abstract String getStoryElementName();

    @Override
    public void startElement(
        String aUri, String aLocalName, 
        String aQName, Attributes aAttributes) 
    throws SAXException {
        handler = handler.startElement(aLocalName);
    }

    @Override
    public void characters(char[] aCh, int aStart, int aLength) 
    throws SAXException {
        handler = handler.characters(aCh, aStart, aLength);
    }

    @Override
    public void endElement(String aUri, String aLocalName, String aQName) 
    throws SAXException {
        handler = handler.endElement(aLocalName);
    }

    public List&amp;lt;Story&gt; getStories() {
        return stories;
    }

    private Handler newDefaultHandler() {
        return new Handler() {
            @Override
            public Handler startElement(String aName) {
                if (aName.equals(getStoryElementName())) {
                    return newItemHandler(this);
                }
                return this;
            }

            @Override
            public Handler characters(
                char[] aChars, int aStart, int aLength) {
                return this;
            }

            @Override
            public Handler endElement(String aName) {
                return this;
            }
        };
    }

    private Handler newItemHandler(final Handler aParent) {
        stories.add(new StoryImpl());

        return new Handler() {
            @Override
            public Handler startElement(String aName) {
                if ("title".equals(aName)) {
                    return newTitleHandler(this);
                }
                return this;
            }

            @Override
            public Handler characters(
                char[] aChars, int aStart, int aLength) {
                return this;
            }

            @Override
            public Handler endElement(String aName) {
                if (getStoryElementName().equals(aName)) {
                    return aParent;
                }
                return this;
            }
        };
    }

    private Handler newTitleHandler(final Handler aParent) {
        final StringBuilder _title = new StringBuilder();

        return new Handler() {
            @Override
            public Handler startElement(String aName) {
                return this;
            }

            @Override
            public Handler characters(
                char[] aChars, int aStart, int aLength) {
                _title.append(aChars, aStart, aLength);
                return this;
            }

            @Override
            public Handler endElement(String aName) {
                if ("title".equals(aName)) {
                    StoryImpl _s = (StoryImpl) 
                    stories.get(stories.size()-1);
                    _s.setTitle(_title.toString());
                    return aParent;
                }
                return this;
            }
        };
    }
}
</code></pre>

<h4>The Android Manifest</h4>

<pre><code>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?&gt;
&lt;manifest 
    xmlns:android="http://schemas.android.com/apk/res/android"
    package="com.knowledgeview.android.ticker"
    android:versionCode="1"
    android:versionName="1.0"&gt;
  &lt;uses-sdk android:minSdkVersion="7" /&gt;
  &lt;uses-permission android:name="android.permission.INTERNET" /&gt;
  &lt;application 
        android:icon="@drawable/icon" 
        android:label="@string/app_name"&gt;
    &lt;receiver android:name=".NewsTicker"&gt;
      &lt;intent-filter&gt;
    &lt;action 
          android:name="android.appwidget.action.APPWIDGET_UPDATE"/&gt;
      &lt;/intent-filter&gt;
      &lt;meta-data 
            android:name="android.appwidget.provider"
    android:resource="@xml/newsticker_widget_info"/&gt;
    &lt;/receiver&gt;
    &lt;service android:name=".NewsTickerDataService"/&gt;
  &lt;/application&gt;
&lt;/manifest&gt;
</code></pre>

<h4>The Widget descriptor</h4>

<pre><code>&lt;appwidget-provider 
      xmlns:android="http://schemas.android.com/apk/res/android"
  android:minWidth="294dp"
  android:minHeight="72dp"
  android:updatePeriodMillis="86400000"
  android:initialLayout="@layout/newsticker_widget"&gt;
&lt;/appwidget-provider&gt;
</code></pre>

<h4>The layout descriptor</h4>

<pre><code>&lt;LinearLayout 
      android:id="@+id/linearLayout1" 
      android:layout_width="fill_parent" 
      android:layout_height="fill_parent" 
      xmlns:android="http://schemas.android.com/apk/res/android"&gt;
  &lt;TextView
    android:textAppearance="?android:attr/textAppearanceSmall"
    android:id="@+id/title"
    android:text="TextView"
    android:textSize="10sp"
    android:textColor="#fff"
    android:layout_height="60dp"
    android:layout_width="fill_parent"
    android:background="#c333"
    android:padding="3dp"
    android:layout_margin="5dp"&gt;
  &lt;/TextView&gt;
&lt;/LinearLayout&gt;
</code></pre>
]]></description>
          <category>Android</category>
          <category>Desktop Widget</category>
          <category>Twitter</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Replicating Java threading issues between machines with different cpu counts]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/replicating_java_threading_issues_between_machines_with_different_cpu_counts.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/replicating_java_threading_issues_between_machines_with_different_cpu_counts.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Today I had a problem where a multi-threaded testcase which runs fine on my 8-core dev box failed when committed to the single-cpu build-server.</p>

<p>To replicate I needed to run on a single-cpu but I didn't want to commit more potentially broken tests to source-control and run repeatedly breaking builds on the build-server.</p>

<p>I discovered that its possible to bind an exec'd process to a single CPU in newer 'nix's using taskset. Invoking my maven build using taskset to bind the test-run to a single CPU core replicated the failure immediately, and from there it was an easy fix. Here's the cmdline to bind a maven build to a single CPU (I'm running Ubuntu, YMMV):</p>

<pre><code>taskset -pc 0 mvn clean test
</code></pre>

<p>tasket is part of schedutils, which you may or may not have installed. It was installed on my machine already, possibly because of other things i've installed in the past. If needed you can install it with:</p>

<pre><code>sudo apt-get install schedutils
</code></pre>

<p>It basically sets processor affinity by setting some process properties that tell the linux cpu scheduler to only allow the process to run on the stated CPU's.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>CPU affinity</category>
          <category>Linux</category>
          <category>Java</category>
          <category>Threading</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[JQuery + HtmlUnit = runtimeError messages galore]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/jquery_htmlunit_runtimeerror_messages_galore.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/jquery_htmlunit_runtimeerror_messages_galore.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>For those who don't care about the back-story and just want the solution: switch the user-agent to Firefox by using the WebClient constructor that takes a BrowserVersion parameter.</p>

<p>...
One of my colleagues wrote a htmlunit test that involved swiftly navigating through a set of pages. The test checked the behaviour was correct and passed just fine, but left behind a very large number of messages like this:</p>

<pre><code>runtimeError: message=
  [The data necessary to complete this operation is not yet available.]
  sourceName=[http://localhost:10821/js/jquery-1.6.1.js] line=[16]
  lineSource=[null] lineOffset=[0]
</code></pre>

<p>This was looking pretty nasty in the hudson and mvn build logs, so I investigated a little to see if I could get rid of it.</p>

<p>First step was to try to figure out what part of the jquery script was triggering the problem, but of course we are using the minified jquery script, so it was impossible to find the problem on line 16 (line 16 is jquery).</p>

<p>Replacing the minified script with the "source" version I get the same error reported at line 923. It's doing the following check:</p>

<pre><code>// The DOM ready check for Internet Explorer
function doScrollCheck() {
 if ( jQuery.isReady ) {
  return;
 }

 try {
  // If IE is used, use the trick by Diego Perini
  // http://javascript.nwbox.com/IEContentLoaded/
     document.documentElement.doScroll("left");
 } catch(e) {
  setTimeout( doScrollCheck, 1 );
  return;
 }

 // and execute any waiting functions
 jQuery.ready();
}
</code></pre>

<p>Line 923 is the one inside the try block. Of course, this is a an IE specific check, and the default user-agent mimicked by HtmlUnit is Internet Explorer 7 - and yes, we were using the default.</p>

<p>You can change the default by passing a BrowserVersion parameter to the WebClient constructor. Switch to Firefox 3 or 3.6 and the problem goes away, switch to IE8 and it gets worse (test fails) - although it seems this is for different reasons, not related to the doScrollCheck. Can't even escape browser version troubles when not using a browser :(</p>

<p>Incidentally I <a href="http://www.andismith.com/blog/2011/11/25-dev-tool-secrets/">discovered recently</a> that many of the latest browsers and developer plugins can "unminify" javascript on the fly.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>JQuery</category>
          <category>HtmlUnit</category>
          <category>runtimeerror</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2011 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Unit Testing code written in "Tell, Don't Ask" style]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/unit_testing_code_written_in_tell_don_t_ask_style.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/unit_testing_code_written_in_tell_don_t_ask_style.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>More and more I find myself enjoying the "Tell, Don't Ask" style of programming, to the extent that recently I've been challenging myself to write all my code that way. </p>

<p>This brought up an interesting discussion while working on a proto-type with an excellent developer I've known and worked with for years - how do you test code written in this style?</p>

<h3>Setting the scene</h3>

<p>The idea of the proto-type was to play with and test out several Entity-Extraction and Text-Clustering algorithms - some that we had researched, some using existing libraries, and others of our own devising. We collected a few dozen Mb-worth of sample data to toy with, and I knocked up a quick harness to feed the test data into the Entity-Extraction and Test-Clustering routines, which just needed to implement a bunch of Java interfaces I'd written (using "Tell, Don't Ask" style). Each of us then proceeded to implement some of the algorithms, which we plugged in Strategy-Pattern style.</p>

<p>Every so often as we were working, my colleague would turn and say something like "I need to add Xxxx to the Yyyy interface, so I can unit-test my implementation". His feeling was that whilst in principle "Tell, Don't Ask" is laudable, it makes testing very awkward and ungainly.</p>

<p>As a result the interfaces drifted away from "Tell, Don't Ask" so that, whilst they still included the callback-style methods, they now presented a more typical "Ask" style API too - a simple example being: implementing <code>Iterable&lt;T&gt;</code> as well as providing <code>each(T)</code> methods.</p>

<h3>Example Tests</h3>

<p>Let's look at a simple example of the kind of tests that appear to be made difficult due to the "Tell, Don't Ask" style. Note that I'm using junit 3.8 style for these examples.</p>

<p>Say we have a Stuff interface, which is an immutable container of Thing's, and a ThingMaker that creates many Thing's and returns them packed in a Stuff.  Here are the "Tell, Don't Ask" interfaces we might have started off with:</p>

<pre><code>  public interface Thing {
    public String getName();
    public void doThings();
  }

  public interface ThingCallback {
    public void with(Thing thing);
  }

  public interface Stuff {
    public void each(ThingCallback callback);
  }

  public interface ThingMaker {
    public Stuff makeThings(int howMany);
  }
</code></pre>

<p>Pretty straight-forward. Now, lets see what happens when we want to test that when we ask the ThingMaker to make two Thing's, we actually get two non-null Thing's. Here's what the test method might look like:</p>

<pre><code>public void testMakesCorrectNumberOfThings() {
  ThingMaker tm = new SimpleThingMaker();
  Stuff result = tm.makeThings(2);

  final boolean[] calledBack = new boolean[1];
  final int[] count = new int[1];

  result.each(new ThingCallback() {
    public void with(Thing thing) {
      calledBack[0] = true;
      if (thing != null) {
        count[0] = count[0]++;
      }
    }
  });

  assertTrue(calledBack[0]);
  assertEquals(2, count.length);
}
</code></pre>

<p>Yikes, that's pretty nasty. What's all that nonsense with the final arrays? Well, given that we're working in an anonymous inner class (the callback) we can't just update a boolean or an int that we've declared in the enclosing scope, the only option we have is to cheat and use final variables that have mutable content - arrays are a cheap way to do that. But I think you'll agree this is hideous.</p>

<p>An alternative is to make the inner class do the checking and counting. To do that we have to raise its profile somewhat, to make it a named inner class:</p>

<pre><code>  class TestThingCallback implements ThingCallback {
    boolean called;
    int count;

    public void with(Thing thing) {
      called = true;
      count++;
    }
  }

  public void testMakesCorrectNumberOfThings() {
    ThingMaker tm = new SimpleThingMaker();
    Stuff result = tm.makeThings(2);

    TestThingCallback cb = new TestThingCallback();
    result.each(cb);

    assertTrue(cb.called);
    assertEquals(2, cb.count);
  }
</code></pre>

<p>OK, well that's a lot better, but the effort of making these "Test Spy" objects grows very quickly, and although this is more readable it somehow feels less concise, and by moving code outside of the test-method it makes it just that little bit more awkward to read.</p>

<p>I think this shows that "classical" unit testing of "Tell, Don't Ask" style code is actually awkward enough to want to find a better way. But can we do any better? Absolutely ...</p>

<h3>Enter, jMock</h3>

<p>jMock is an astonishingly useful tool in the testing arsenal. It makes truly unit testing your code possible without masses of work creating Test Double's, because it does all the grunt work for you. Lets quickly re-write our test using jmock.</p>

<pre><code>  public class TestCaseThingMaker extends MockObjectTestCase {
    public void testMakesCorrectNumberOfThings() {
      final ThingCallback callback = mock(ThingCallback.class);
      checking(new Expectations(){{
        exactly(2).of(callback).each(with(any(Thing.class)));
      }});

      ThingMaker tm = new SimpleThingMaker();
      Stuff result = tm.makeThings(2);
      result.each(callback);
    }
  }
</code></pre>

<p>Some of that might need a little explanation, so here goes:</p>

<p>The first thing we do inside our test method is create a "mock" instance of the ThingCallback interface. jMock does this for you in the invocation of the mock method.</p>

<p>Next we set up our "expectations" of what will happen to the mock ThingCallback during our test. The slightly funky syntax with the double braces is just an instance initializer on an anonymous inner class. The interesting bit is the declaration of what we expect to happen to our mock object - this is the bit inside those {{ ... }} written in jMock's intuitive internal DSL. To understand it you just have to read the whole line from left to right - we're expecting exactly 2 invocations of callback.each() with any instance of Thing.</p>

<p>Once we've set up our expectations it only remains to build the object under test - SimpleThingMaker - and invoke the methods we want to test.
If you are staring at that and wondering how JMock knows that the test is finished and the expectations should have been met (and that it should fail the test if not), notice that I'm using the JUnit-3 integration here - extending MockObjectTestCase - and the behind the scenes plumbing is taking care of that last step for me. </p>

<p>If you're using the JUnit-4 integration you need to explicitly invoke assertIsSatisfied on the mock object context (org.jmock.Mockery) which supplied your mock objects.
jMock takes a little getting used to, as it involves quite a different way of thinking about your test. If you want to write good tests with it it certainly involves considerable effort to learn how to use it well (its easy to use it badly and end up with tests which are very difficult to understand). Once you get used to it though, it really does make tests much easier to write and, more importantly, to read.</p>

<p>I find that jMock really comes into its own when testing Tell, Don't Ask code - the code under test is clean and, by nature of the improved data-hiding, more robust, whilst jMock provides a very neat way to test that code with a minimum of fuss and boiler-plate. </p>

<p><em>UPDATE:</em> After ruminating on this for a while I came to the conclusion that JMock is so good at testing "Tell, don't ask" code that I was sure the designers of JMock must have set out with that in mind. I found a very nice post from @natpryce (one of the JMock authors) which confirmed my suspicions - Nat describes tell don't ask very succinctly:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>"...objects tell each other what to do by sending commands to one another, they don't ask each other for information and then make decisions upon the results of those queries. </p>
  
  <p>The end result of this style is that it is easy to swap one object for another that can respond to the same commands but in a different way. This is because the behaviour of one object is not tied to the internal structure of the objects that it talks to."</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Nat goes on to say that the only way to test tell-dont-ask code is to see how the state of the world is affected when objects are told to do something (because you can't ask them about their state), and that this is best achieved with mock objects, whereas "train wreck" code (Nat's description of code that is not written tell-dont-ask style, and commonly violates demeter's law) is hard to test with mock objects.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>TDD</category>
          <category>Unit Testing</category>
          <category>Tell Dont Ask</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[ElasticSearch vs SOLRCloud]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/elasticsearch_vs_solrcloud.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/elasticsearch_vs_solrcloud.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>For an upcoming work project I need a scalable search platform - scalable to tens or hundreds of millions of documents (news articles), and millions of queries per day. We're a (mostly) Java shop, and have a lot of experience with Lucene, so two solutions that pique my curiosity are SOLRCloud (SOLR + ZooKeeper) and ElasticSearch.</p>

<h3>Initial Impressions - ElasticSearch</h3>

<p>ElasticSearch is impressive. Its clean, simple, and elegant. For those who are familiar with Compass, ElasticSearch can be considered as Compass 3.0 (quoting Shay Bannon, author of Compass). ElasticSearch has been under development for about 9 months at time of writing, and is currently at version 0.15. It appears to be very actively developed, with new features and fixes flowing steadily. </p>

<p>My main worry at this point is that there appears to be only one "resource" active on the project - Shay Bannon (@kimchy) himself, who seems to be architect, developer, documentation-writer, and a prolific commenter on forums.</p>

<h4>Noteworthy features include:</h4>

<ul>
<li>Document-oriented / Schema-free (JSON documents)</li>
<li>Store, retrieve, index and search multiple versions of documents</li>
<li>Self-hosting RESTful web-service api</li>
<li>Exposes the full power of lucene queries</li>
<li>Multiple Indexes in one cluster (described as Multi-Tenancy)</li>
<li>Built from the ground-up with scalability and distributed-operation in mind - supporting distributed search, automatic fail-over and re-balancing, with no single point of failure</li>
<li>Support for async write/backup to shared storage (Gateway, in ElasticSearch parlance)</li>
<li>"Percolator" (aka. prospective search)</li>
</ul>

<h3>Initial Impressions - SOLRCloud</h3>

<p>SOLR is a project from the same (Apache) stable as Lucene itself, and the projects have recently merged to some degree. SOLRCloud is an extension that integrates ZooKeeper with SOLR with the express aim of "enabling and simplifying the creation and use of Solr clusters."</p>

<p>SOLRCloud is described as "still under development", ie., not yet a GA release. </p>

<h4>Currently proclaimed features include:</h4>

<ul>
<li>Central configuration of the entire cluster</li>
<li>Automatic load-balancing and fail-over for queries</li>
<li>ZooKeeper integration for cluster coordination and configuration (not sure I would have listed that as a feature personally!)</li>
<li>I'll add that SOLRCloud is part of the SOLR code-base, and is being developed by core Lucene and SOLR committers including Mark Miller and Yonik Seeley. This can only be a good thing :). On top of all that, SOLR has been around for a good long time now, so it is battle-tested and there's lots of information available (including numerous books).</li>
</ul>

<p>That said, I still have two big worries about SOLRCloud:
* Setup/deployment just sounds fiddly - it is recommended not to deploy zookeeper embedded with SOLR (though I cannot find any explanation to back up that recommendation), which means you need both a ZooKeeper ensemble - multiple ZooKeeper instances - and a SOLRCloud ... er ... cloud.
* No GA release as yet, and no roadmap that I can find (this is the closest I got).</p>

<h3>Next Steps</h3>

<p>My next steps are to dive in to both technologies and really get to see which best suits our needs, and really how difficult these things are likely to be to manage in a medium/large-scale deployment.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>ElasticSearch</category>
          <category>SOLRCloud</category>
          <category>Lucene</category>
          <category>Search</category>
          <category>Scalability</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Progressive Enhancement with GWT, part 3]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/progressive_enhancement_with_gwt_part_3.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/progressive_enhancement_with_gwt_part_3.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>UPDATE: Since writing this series I have published the source of <a href="http://steveliles.github.com/gwt_progressive.html"><code>gwt.progressive</code> at github</a>.</p>

<p>This is the third part in a series, following my thoughts on using GWT in SEO'able web applications. The other parts in the series are <a href="progressive_enhancement_with_gwt_part_1.html">part 1</a> and <a href="progressive_enhancement_with_gwt_part_2.html">part 2</a>.</p>

<p>In my previous posts I described an idea for progressive enhancement using GWT -  "activating" server-generated html, to combine GWT goodness with an SEO friendly server-generated website, and my findings after some initial trials. </p>

<p>One of the problems I described in that second post was that it would be very difficult to work with these widgets if nested widgets could not be automatically (or at least easily) bound to fields within this widget.</p>

<p>After a little playing around and learning about GWT Generators I now have what seems like a nice solution, using a Generator to do almost all of the donkey work. Think of it like UiBinder, but with the templates provided at runtime (courtesy of the server). Here's an example class that automatically binds sub-widgets - an Image in this case - to a field of that class:</p>

<pre><code>public class MyWidget extends Widget {

    interface MyActivator extends ElementActivator&lt;MyWidget&gt; {}
    private static MyActivator activator = GWT.create(MyActivator.class);

    @RuntimeUiField(tag="img", cssClass="small") Image small;

    public MyWidget(Element anElement) {
        // this will set our element and bind our image field.
        setElement(activator.activate(this, anElement));

        // now we can play with our fields.
        small.addClickHandler(new ClickHandler() {
            public void onClick(ClickEvent aEvent) {
                Window.alert("clicked!");
            }
        });
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>This class will bind onto any html that has an image tag somewhere in its inner-html, for example:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;div&gt; &lt;!-- Say our MyWidget is bound here --&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;
          &lt;!-- will be bound to our Image widget --&gt;
      &lt;img class="small" src="/images/image.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Anyone familiar with UiBinder will recognize the pattern I've used for the "activator":</p>

<ul>
<li>Extend an interface with no methods
<code>interface MyActivator extends ElementActivator&lt;MyWidget&gt; {}</code></li>
<li>GWT.create() an instance of that interface
<code>private static MyActivator activator = GWT.create(MyActivator.class);</code></li>
<li>Then use it to initialize your widget
<code>setElement(activator.activate(this, anElement));</code></li>
</ul>

<p>The nice thing about this is we can automatically bind as many widgets as we like onto various sites within the inner-html of our current widget's element. It doesn't mess with the structure (unless you explicitly do so after the binding is done for you), and you can have as much other html within the elements as you like - it will just be left alone, which gives your designers the flexibility to change the layout quite a lot without necessarily needing to re-compile your GWT code. </p>

<p>Currently I have my generator set up to allow your widgets to bind to a choice of tag-name or css-class or both, for example:</p>

<pre><code>// bind to the first &amp;lt;div&gt; found by breadth-first 
// search of child elements
@RuntimeUiField(tag="div") Label label;

// bind to first element with class="my-widget" 
// found by breadth-first search
@RuntimeUiField(cssClass="my-widget") Label label;

// bind to first &amp;lt;div&gt; with class="my-widget" 
// found by breadth-first search
@RuntimeUiField(tag="div", cssClass="my-widget") Label label;
</code></pre>

<p>Notice in my examples so far I'm binding standard GWT widgets onto the nested elements. This works for the elements I've used in these examples because they all have a <code>public static Type wrap(Element anElement)</code> method which allows those widgets to be bound onto elements that are already attached to the DOM.</p>

<p>It is also possible to bind widgets of your own making in one of two ways:</p>

<ol>
<li>Create a wrap method like 
<code>public static MyWidget wrap(Element anElement)</code></li>
<li>Create a single-argument public Constructor that accepts an <code>Element</code> as its argument.</li>
</ol>

<p>Activate-able widgets can be nested within other such widgets - with no limits that I am aware of so far - and it is also possible to assign nested widgets to a List field in the enclosing widget, like this:</p>

<pre><code>@RuntimeUiField(tag="img") List&lt;Image&gt; images;
</code></pre>

<p>This will search recursively for any <code>&lt;img&gt;</code> tags inside the enclosing widget's element and bind them all to Image widget's that will be added to the List. The current limitations here are that the List must be declared either as List or ArrayList, and parameterized with a concrete type that meets the criteria defined above (i.e. has a static <code>wrap(Element)</code> method, or a single-arg constructor that takes an <code>Element</code> as the argument).</p>

<p>A remaining question is how to bind the outer-most Widget. Currently I'm doing that using the DOM scanning code I wrote during earlier experiments and which I'm also using in the automatic scanning process set up by the Generator. For example to find the outer-most widgets and kick off the binding process I have something like this in my EntryPoint:</p>

<pre><code>public void onModuleLoad() {
    List&lt;MyWidget&gt; _myWidgets = new ArrayList&lt;mywidget&gt;();
    for (Element _e : Elements.getByCssClass("outer-most-widget")) {
        new MyWidget(_e);
    }
    // do stuff with our widgets ...
}
</code></pre>

<p>I think of this as very similar to the RootPanel situation - "normal" GWT apps kick off by getting a RootPanel(body tag) or RootPanel's (looked up by id), to which everything else is added. It would be nice to hide away some of that scanning code inside a "top-level" widget - much like RootPanel does for the normal case. I can imagine this might look something like:</p>

<pre><code>public void onModuleLoad() {
    Page _page = Page.activate();
    _page.doStuffWithWidgets();
    // ...
}
</code></pre>

<p>I still have lots of things to figure out and questions to answer, for example:</p>

<ul>
<li>What's the performance like when binding many hundreds of widgets?</li>
<li>How will this really work when I make ajax requests for more data? (should I make ajax requests for html snippets which I add to the DOM and then bind onto, or switch to json for ajax requests and make my widgets able to replicate themselves from an initial html template?)</li>
<li>What's the best way to divide labour between developers and designers, and for them to organize their interaction? (Ideally I'd like there to be something of a cycle between them, where the designer can rough-out a page design, agree the componentisation with the developer, the developer knocks out some components and a build which the designer can use to activate their static designs, add fidelity, work on other pages with the same components, etc).</li>
<li>Where is the sweet-spot between creating high-fidelity html server-side and decorating it client-side using GWT? Should the GWT components really be just for adding dynamism, or is it a good idea to use them to build additional html sweetness? - I mean the server could dish out html that is more of a model than a view (just enough "view" to satisfy SEO), and the GWT layer acts as a client-side controller and view (<a href="http://www.thinserverarchitecture.com/home">SOFEA/TSA</a> with a nod to SEO).</li>
</ul>

<p>I'll try to keep posting as I work things out.</p>

<p>This probably belongs in a separate post, but with reference to that last point on TSA (Thin Server Architecture) - the working group list the following points to define the concept:</p>

<blockquote>
  <ol>
  <li>Do not use server-side templating to create the web page.</li>
  <li>Use a classical and simple client-server model, where the client runs in the browser.</li>
  <li>Separate concerns using protocol between client and server and get a much more efficient and less costly development model.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>I'm right behind them on (2) and (3), and also on (1) for "enterprise" apps where SEO is a non-goal. However, for an app that needs SEO, (1) is a deal-breaker, so I'd offer this alternative 1st rule instead:</p>

<ol>
<li>Use server-side templating to produce a model for the client to consume which minimally satisfies the needs of SEO.</li>
</ol>
]]></description>
          <category>ajax</category>
          <category>designer</category>
          <category>gwt</category>
          <category>progressive enhancement</category>
          <category>SEO</category>
          <category>SOFEA</category>
          <category>TSA</category>
          <category>UiBinder</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Installing fonts in Ubuntu]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/installing_fonts_in_ubuntu.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/installing_fonts_in_ubuntu.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Installing fonts in ubuntu is very easy these days - just open a ttf file and you are presented with a nice sample of the font (quick brown fox style), and a button in the bottom right corner to install the font.</p>

<p>Nice'n'easy, but you're not quite done yet. You'll definitely need to restart running apps before the font becomes available to them, and quite possibly you'll need to rebuild the font cache, which you can do by rebooting (hah!) or:</p>

<pre><code>sudo fccache -fv
</code></pre>

<p>btw., check out <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:EurostileSpec.svg">Eurostile</a>. Its about 50 years old, but nonetheless is one of the most gorgeous fonts i've ever seen.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>fonts</category>
          <category>ubuntu</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Progressive Enhancement with GWT, part 2]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/progressive_enhancement_with_gwt_part_2.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/progressive_enhancement_with_gwt_part_2.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>UPDATE: Since writing this series I have published the source of <a href="http://steveliles.github.com/gwt_progressive.html"><code>gwt.progressive</code> at github</a>.</p>

<p>This is the second part in a series, following my thoughts on using GWT in SEO'able web applications. The other parts in the series are <a href="progressive_enhancement_with_gwt_part_1.html">part 1</a> and <a href="progressive_enhancement_with_gwt_part_3.html">part 3</a>.</p>

<p>Since my earlier post, I spent a little time (only a few hours really, so far) trying a few things out. Here's a smattering of things I learned...</p>

<p>Scanning for elements and binding widgets onto them is easy. Making those widgets behave just like widgets in any normal GWT app needs a little more work.</p>

<h3>Who's the daddy?</h3>

<p>One big problem to get around is that normally GWT widgets are attached via a hierarchy of other widgets (parents) leading back to the RootPanel, whereas when you bind onto some arbitrary element that is already on the page you don't get this hierarchy for free.</p>

<p>When widgets are added to a parent widget some magic happens to set up things like the eventing system. Without that magic you can add as much event-handling plumbing as you like, but it won't work because your widget isn't wired into the eventing system.</p>

<p>Actually getting around this is not all that difficult. Simply invoking onAttach() will wire up your widget, though its a little unpleasant to have to do that.</p>

<p>Another problem with the lack of hierarchy is, well, there's no hierarchy. Things that you would normally do in GWT widgets - like adding, removing or replacing child widgets - gets a little trickier. If you want to use the technique recursively (and why wouldn't you?), you need to allow widgets to bind to elements inside other widgets without causing them to be removed from and re-attached to the DOM, but crucially you still need to add them as 'logical' children of the parent widget, otherwise the parent knows nothing about the child widgets and can't do any of those "normal" operations with them.</p>

<p>To do that there are two problems to overcome:</p>

<ol>
<li>The parent needs to have the children added to it, so that the set of child widgets is known and available for manipulation (say by extending ComplexPanel and using the getChildren() method).</li>
<li>Some of the child widgets might need hard, typed references in the parent widget to allow direct manipulation of the child widget - just like in a "normal" GWT widget you would keep a reference to the Button you added in the constructor in order that you can bind ClickHandler's to it or toggle its enabled-ness.</li>
</ol>

<p>Point 1 is easily solved - any widget that wants to play this way needs to support adding other widgets without triggering an attachment to the current element. When you add a normal child widget to a normal  parent widget, the child is detached from its current parent - logically and physically - so that its html element is actually inserted into the DOM under the parent's element. This is not what we want when binding onto a template - we just want the logical attachment step, so we need to support an add method something like:</p>

<pre><code>public void logicalAdd(Widget aWidget) {
  getChildren().add(aWidget);
  adopt(aWidget);     
}
</code></pre>

<p>I've yet to try to solve point 2. So far I've built:</p>

<ul>
<li>Tools to help with scanning for elements to bind to, and then binding the right widget.</li>
<li>Plumbing to allow recursively binding widgets with logical hierarchy intact (point 1 above).</li>
<li>An example that binds widgets recursively - an outer container, an inner container, and a bunch of widgets inside that are manipulated by the inner container.</li>
</ul>

<p>I'll try to update the post with an example at some point. Meanwhile my next challenge is to solve point 2 such that widget developers can build their widgets in a fairly typical GWT way.</p>

<p>As an aside, I lay awake for a while last night pondering the ability to give designers a client-side templating system, where they can write the html for a component once (declaring it to be a template, which may include recursive binding points for GWT-activated widgets) and then re-use it elsewhere within their html by reference to the template. I'm sure this would be possible, though its utility might extend only to mock-ups.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>ajax</category>
          <category>designer</category>
          <category>gwt</category>
          <category>progressive enhancement</category>
          <category>SEO</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Progressive Enhancement with GWT, part 1]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/progressive_enhancement_with_gwt_part_1.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/progressive_enhancement_with_gwt_part_1.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>This is the first part in a series, following my thoughts on using GWT in SEO'able web applications. The other parts in the series are <a href="progressive_enhancement_with_gwt_part_2.html">part 2</a> and <a href="progressive_enhancement_with_gwt_part_3.html">part 3</a>.</p>

<p>GWT Is a superb framework for developing complex, componentized html &amp; javascript widgets.  You can have your cake and eat it:</p>

<ul>
<li>Drop down into native javascript as and when you feel the need</li>
<li>Integrate easily with native js components and libraries</li>
<li>Use GWT components relatively easily from native javascript</li>
<li>Create super-condensed, fast, platform-specific code, easily</li>
<li>All the benefits of Java's static type-system, packages, and tooling to manage and refactor your code</li>
<li>It is very tempting to go for an all-out GWT user-interface, which is great if what you want is a super-snazzy Rich-Internet-Application which packs down into very small and extremely cacheable js bundles that fetch data asynchronously from the server, and you don't mind re-compiling your user-interface to make even a very small change.</li>
</ul>

<p>It isn't so great when:</p>

<ul>
<li>You need to expose the content of your site for search-engines to index (The SEO Problem).</li>
<li>You want to leverage the html and css skills of your UI designers, and to be able to generate more flexible layouts without requiring a re-compile (The Design Problem).</li>
</ul>

<h2>The SEO Problem</h2>

<p>To a search engine, GWT apps just look like a big fat lump of dense javascript. Nothing to see here, move along. Its a similar problem for any web-app that uses ajax to collect data from the server, but the problem is magnified with GWT due to the fact that the entire application tends to present as a large lump of dense javascript, whereas many other ajax technologies typically involve some amount of server-side content rendering that can make the site at least partially visible to crawlers.</p>

<p>Google have a recommendation for how to get around the problems of SEO for ajax applications, which entails a special url form and the creation of "html snapshots" - effectively a parallel, ajax-disabled site that the crawler can index. This seems to me to be a workable but irritating solution that involves doing a lot of extra work just to allow a search engine to crawl the site. Its effectively just a Google-approved cloaking method. Also it isn't clear to me whether any other search engines than Google support this approach.</p>

<h2>The Design Problem</h2>

<p>Don't get me wrong, its not as bad as all that. You can, of course, leverage your UI/UX designer's talents when building GWT apps. They can produce designs that the GWT developers base their components on, and with UIBinder the html fragments produced by a designer can be used in large chunks, but there is always some disconnect between what the designers produce and what is actually output by the application - usually because there is a developer translating the designer's work into GWT components.</p>

<p>In retrospect, having built a number of "monolithic" GWT applications, it seems to me that what we're missing is a way to step back just a little from the "GWT does everything" mind-set, and instead to leverage GWT where it is best suited, and something a little more flexible where GWT can be too restrictive - for example when laying out high level components on a page it would be advantageous to be able to escape from the restrictions of having to compile that page layout into js, and instead work at the level of straight-forward declarative markup.</p>

<h2>Introducing "GWT-Activated Pages"</h2>

<p>How can we solve these two issues? One idea I've been toying with, is to use GWT for progressive enhancement of simple html + css, and goes as follows:</p>

<p>Rather than try to build two almost parallel versions of your application (one for SEO, one for real users), why not build one with a layered approach that allows graceful degradation for browsers with javascript disabled (of which search-engines could be considered a sub-set).</p>

<p>The base-layer that non-javascript browsers would render, and which search-engines would see, would be generated  by some typical server-side technology - php, jsp, struts, jfaces, ... take your pick. This would build a "wireframe" of your page, giving it a basic shape and layout, and filling in some starter content. The markup would ideally be meaningful, in the sense that headings would appear in <code>&lt;h1&gt;</code> tags to indicate that they are headings, rather than to give them any particular styling.</p>

<p>This base layer would be something that designers could work on directly, including any and all css styling.</p>

<p>The second layer would be a set of GWT widgets that "activate" or progressively enhance the page, by scanning the DOM for certain signs that denote activateable sections of markup. When the base page loads, GWT widgets search for elements to bind themselves to. When a widget finds such an element it binds to it and "activates" it. Activation could mean anything from completely changing the html markup, to binding event-listeners, to handling interaction with ajax data loading from the server.</p>

<p>Here's a simple example "base" layer:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;Page Header&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;ol class="gwt-navigation-widget"&gt;
      &lt;!-- the listitems are generated server side --&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=".."&gt;Home&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=".."&gt;News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=".."&gt;Videos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=".."&gt;Photos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=".."&gt;About&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
    &lt;ol class="gwt-news-ticker-widget"&gt;
      &lt;!-- the listitems are generated server side --&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;News story 1&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;News story 2&lt;/li&gt;
      ...
      &lt;!-- this last listitem gives a link that 
               a search engine can follow to get more data --&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=".."&gt;older stories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;


    &lt;script type="text/javascript" language="javascript" 
                src="widgets/navigation-widget.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script type="text/javascript" language="javascript" 
                src="widgets/news-ticker-widget.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Notice the elements with css class-names prefixed with "gwt-". These are the signs that our gwt widgets will be looking for in order to know which elements they should activate.</p>

<p>As you probably guessed, the navigation widget would detect any elements with a class-name matching "gwt-navigation-widget", while the news-ticker will search for "gwt-news-ticker-widget".</p>

<p>OK, so what do we get for our troubles? Well, several things potentially:</p>

<ul>
<li>One request to the server to get our initial page full of data (rather than multiple widgets requesting async loading of little chunks of data)</li>
<li>A page that contains the data and is search-engine friendly, allowing pages deep within your app to indexed by search-engines</li>
<li>A very clear separation of widgets and page layout, allowing you more flexibility to change the page layout without GWT re-compile</li>
<li>Flexibility in dividing work between designers and developers:
<ul><li>designers can focus on the design-heavy html and css work, and the overall page layout</li>
<li>developers can focus on interaction with the server, complex widget behaviour, etc.</li></ul></li>
<li>Upon finding an element to bind to, the widget would:
<ul><li>Examine the content of the element - this will very likely be the source of its initial configuration and/or data-set, and also might include some information about how to load more content, as in the news-ticker example whose last <li> is a link to "older stories". I'm sure it would be a good idea to make this even more explicit, but like I said this is supposed to be a simple example :)</li>
<li>Replace or modify the content of the element - perhaps the widget displays a very complicated UI, so it removes the html and replaces it with something nifty that it generates, or maybe it just adds some decoration in the form of small visible changes, or perhaps it binds a bunch of event handlers to do neat tricks like adding gesture handling for touch-screen users. It seems that it would be perfectly possible to bind widgets inside widgets in this way, although at some point you would probably want to control the binding order such that an outer widget binds before an inner one. One way to do this might be to have a page-activator that seeks elements that want to be activated, and which all widgets are registered with. This could be described nicely as a Pattern.</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<p>In my simple example I showed the scripts being loaded separately, just for clarity, but I'm sure you wouldn't want to load each widget as a separate script - that would lose a good chunk of GWT's advantage. Rather, the whole widget-set could be loaded as one script, cached forever, and used all over.</p>

<p>Now, if you want to see an example of GWT-activated pages at work, just take a look at my older post on <a href="3d_graphics_using_the_html5_canvas.html">rendering 3D Rubiks Cubes with GWT and HTML5 Canvas</a>, where the rubik's cubes are rendered by a gwt widget that "activates" a <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> element containing the configuration for the cube.</p>

<p>OK, but what are the down-sides? Here's a few...</p>

<ul>
<li>Compiler no longer has visibility across the whole UI.</li>
<li>Messaging between components becomes more difficult (but not impossible). This has its advantages too - it forces low coupling. Messaging via OpenAjax Hub or similar would be worth considering.</li>
<li>It's more work - in some naive ways - than a straight-out GWT UI, and many would argue why bother to use GWT at all if you need SEO (depends on your skill-set and the complexity of the components you're building in my view).</li>
<li>I'm sure that there are others which I'm currently blind to ... I need to try to build some more complex and interesting examples to find these out.</li>
</ul>

<p>tl;dr ?</p>
]]></description>
          <category>ajax</category>
          <category>designer</category>
          <category>gwt</category>
          <category>seo</category>
          <category>progressive enhancement</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Reading List, 17-01-2011]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/reading_list_17_01_2011.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/reading_list_17_01_2011.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>I love it when I get a box from Amazon. Today's new arrivals: five (count 'em) new tech books:
<br />
<table cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" style="border:0px; padding:0px; margin:0px;"><tr>
<td><br />
<a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0137030428?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=stlibl-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0137030428"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_hG-kje6-TJM/TTRSN0S4WzI/AAAAAAAAHBU/AAA_9H_2vL0/s1600/scalability.jpg" /></a><br />
</td>
<td><br />
<a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0596153813?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=stlibl-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0596153813"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_hG-kje6-TJM/TTRSM-wm1rI/AAAAAAAAHBI/00iR-DpdRQk/s1600/semantic.jpg" /></a><br />
</td>
<td><br />
<a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0596805829?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=stlibl-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0596805829"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_hG-kje6-TJM/TTRSNFhjZNI/AAAAAAAAHBM/6cPI6CzmaMU/s1600/rest.jpg" /></a><br />
</td>
<td><br />
<a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0321601912?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=stlibl-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0321601912"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_hG-kje6-TJM/TTRSNs49zyI/AAAAAAAAHBQ/AN8rHxCWlpY/s1600/delivery.jpg" /></a><br />
</td>
<td><br />
<a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0321712943?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=stlibl-21&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=19450&amp;creativeASIN=0321712943"><img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_hG-kje6-TJM/TTRSOD2aquI/AAAAAAAAHBY/b04xakC9YiI/s1600/dslbook.jpg" /></a><br />
</td>
</tr>
</table><br />
I'm particularly intrigued to read "The Art of Scalability" - I've never come across a book quite like this that addresses the organisational aspects of scaling a company and processes alongside the architectural aspects of developing scalable software.</p>
]]></description>
          <category>books</category>
          <category>reading list</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title><![CDATA[Linux Distro popularity]]></title>
        <link><![CDATA[http://steveliles.github.com/linux_distro_popularity.html]]></link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://steveliles.github.com/linux_distro_popularity.html</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[<p>Interesting to see how Ubuntu has overtaken its sire Debian in recent years - Google Trends really is amazing.</p>

<p><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_hG-kje6-TJM/TSIqrAJk8gI/AAAAAAAAG_g/e1VdMyp4pJ4/s1600/ubuntu-vs-debian.png" alt="Google Trends chart of Ubuntu (blue), Debian (red), CentOS (green) and Suse (orange)." /></p>

<p><code>Ubuntu (blue), Debian (red), CentOS (green) and Suse (orange)</code></p>

<p>Here's the link to see the full <a href="http://www.google.com/trends?q=ubuntu,+debian,+centos,+suse&amp;ctab=0&amp;geo=all&amp;date=all&amp;sort=0">google-trends page</a> for this comparison.</p>

<p>I love the spikes on the ubuntu line every 6 months - I imagine these coincide with the 6-monthly .4 and .10 releases (April and October).</p>

<p>Interestingly, when I compare Ubuntu with Windows 7 and OSX, OSX loses out strongly to Ubuntu (perhaps I'm using the wrong term, but I tried a number of different combinations), while Win7 is around 3x more popular than Ubuntu.  Also interesting to note how OSX beats Ubuntu in the "news" mentions (below the x-axis) presumably because of the Apple PR machine:</p>

<p><img src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_hG-kje6-TJM/TSIsA8ZS4hI/AAAAAAAAG_k/x90cJQmmGJE/s1600/ubuntu-vs-windows.png" alt="Google Trends chart of Ubuntu (blue), Windows 7 (red), OSX (orange)" /></p>

<p><code>Ubuntu (blue), Windows 7 (red), OSX (orange)</code></p>
]]></description>
          <category>linux</category>
          <category>ubuntu</category>
          <category>centos</category>
          <category>debian</category>
          <category>suse</category>
          <category>distro</category>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[ Steve Liles ]]></dc:creator>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
